<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_vert_gotm_mod" DATE="2012/06/03 00:41:57" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/vertical"><CONTACT EMAIL="mschmidt@io-warnemuende.de"> Martin Schmidt 
</CONTACT><CONTACT EMAIL="Mike.Herzfeld@csiro.au"> Mike Herzfeld
</CONTACT><CONTACT EMAIL="Russell.Fiedler@csiro.au"> Russell Fiedler 
</CONTACT><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> Stephen M. Griffies
</CONTACT><OVERVIEW>
 Vertical viscosity and diffusivity according GOTM.
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 This module contains interfaces to initialize and invoke the 
 Generalized Ocean Turbulence Model (GOTM) parameterizations.
 Full documentation of the schemes available with GOTM 
 can be found at www.gotm.net.

 MOM is distributed with the basic routines from the 4.0
 release of GOTM.  Questions about GOTM should be directed 
 to the GOTM users group at www.gotm.net.  

 This module assumes a twolevel time stepping scheme is used 
 to update the turbulence scalar fields tke and diss. 

 Presently it has only been implemented assuming Bgrid.
 So it needs to be updated for Cgrid layout.  

 Here is a brief outline of the GOTM scheme:

 The non-conservative part of the tke 
 equation is P+B-diss, where P=shear production, 
 B=buoyancy production.  The non-conservative part of 
 the diss equation is a linear combination of tke, 
 P, B and diss. 

 The conservatie part of both tke and diss equations is 
 3D advection.  

 So vertical shear and buoyancy contribute to the 
 source and sinks (respectively) of tke and dissipation. 

 The mixing coefficients are the product of a stability
 function, sqrt(tke), and turbulence length scale (the latter 
 a non-linear function of tke and diss). 

 In the hydro model (i.e., MOM), buoyancy fluxes are the 
 surface boundary conditions for vertical diffusion of temp (heat
 fluxes) and salt (freshwater fluxes), which in turn determine the
 density, and thus enter GOTM via the calculation of buoyancy production.

 Hence, buoyancy fluxes are NOT directly required as surface boundary 
 conditions for GOTM. 

 Wind stress provides the surface boundary condition for vertical 
 momentum mixing in MOM.  This information then enters GOTM 
 via the shear production calculation.  However, wind stress
 can enter the GOTM tke equation as the surface boundary 
 condition for vertical diffusion of tke (i.e. the prescribed, 
 or Dirichlet, condition). This information is typically used in  
 Mellor-Yamada turbulence models. An alternate no-flux (Neumann)
 condition is used in the k-e models, and so do not require wind stress.

 Boundary conditions for vertical diffusion of diss involve roughness,
 tke, and constants (both Neumann and Dirichlet). 

</DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
 Burchard, H., K. Bolding and M. R. Villarreal
 GOTM, a general ocean turbulence model. Theory
 implementation and test cases.
 European Communities, EUR 18745 EN, 1999
 </REFERENCE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_vert_gotm_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  Must be true to use this module. Default is .false. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging.  Default is .false. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="do_turbulence_gotm" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging.  If do_turbulence_gotm=.false., then
  will not invoke the GOTM scheme. Will only advect 
  tke and diss using 3d advection scheme. 
  Default is .true., so that will invoke GOTM scheme.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="do_advection_gotm" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging.  If do_advection_gotm=.false., then
  will not invoke the advection of tke and diss. 
  Default is .true., so that will 3d advect tke and diss. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="write_a_restart" TYPE="logical">
  Set true to write a restart.  False setting only for rare 
  cases where wish to benchmark model without measuring the cost
  of writing restarts and associated chksums.  
  Default is write_a_restart=.true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="advect_gotm_method" TYPE="character">
  For choosing how to advect the GOTM scalar fields tke and diss.
  Options are advect_gotm_method='upwind' (the default) 
              advect_gotm_method='sweby'
  </DATA><DATA NAME="diff_cbt_min" UNITS="m^2/sec" TYPE="real">
  Background diffusivity.  Default is 1.0e-5. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="visc_cbu_min" UNITS="m^2/sec" TYPE="real">
  Background viscosity.  Default is 1.0e-5. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="z0s" UNITS="m" TYPE="real">
  Surface roughness length.  Default is 1m.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="z0b" UNITS="m" TYPE="real">
  Bottom roughness length.  Default is .002m.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="min_tke" UNITS="m^2/s^2" TYPE="real">
  Minimum turbulent kinetic energy.  Default=1.0e-6.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="min_diss" UNITS="m^2/s^3" TYPE="real">
  Minimum energy dissipation.  Default=1.0e-10.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="       constants_mod"/><USE NAME="    diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="             fms_mod"/><USE NAME="          fms_io_mod"/><USE NAME="     mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="             mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="        mtridiagonal"/><USE NAME="          turbulence"/><USE NAME="   ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="     ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="      ocean_util_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_workspace_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_obc_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_vert_gotm_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialization for the MOM wrapper to the GOTM vertical mixing scheme.

 For restarts: 

 We use twolevel time stepping scheme to update tke and diss,
 so only need to read in the taup1_gotm value. 
 call mpp_update_domains since need tke and diss in halos for 
 the advection calculation. 

 We need viscosity and diffusivity saved to restarts in order 
 to update the tke and diss fields within GOTM. 

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="vert_mix_gotm_bgrid" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 This subroutine computes the vertical diffusivity and viscosity 
 according to the GOTM mixing model.

 The tke, diss, NN, and SS arrays are computed on tracer cells.

 Use smf_bgrid since this array uses the primary smf array read in from 
 the coupler in ocean_core/ocean_sbc.F90 when using the FMS coupler.

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="advect_gotm_compute" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Wrapper for advection of GOTM scalar fields tke and diss. 

 Horizontally tke and diss are on tracer cells, so advection just as if 
 they were tracers. 
 Vertically they are between tracer cells. We do not average but shift 
 tke and diss upward to tracer points for vertical advection. At the bottom 
 tke and diss are define by the Dirichlet boundary condition.

 Since use a two-level time stepping scheme for tke and diss,
 it is necessary to advect these scalars with an upwind biased
 advection scheme.

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="advect_gotm_upwind" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 First order upwind to advect GOTM scalar turbulence quantities tke and diss.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="advect_gotm_sweby" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Sweby scheme to advect GOTM scalar turbulence quantities tke and diss.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_vert_gotm_restart" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
  Write out restart files registered through register_restart_file
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_vert_gotm_end" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Save the advection term for restarting the next time step. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
