<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="idealized_bc_mod" DATE="2009/07/21 03:22:49" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/preprocessing/mom4_prep/idealized_bc"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> Z. Liang  </CONTACT><REVIEWER EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> S.M. Griffies </REVIEWER><OVERVIEW>
 For preparing idealized mom4 surface boundary conditions
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 This program prepares idealized surface boundary conditions. The generated data
 contains some or all of the following, temperature, salinity, water flux,
 zonal and meridinal wind stress. The choice of output data is controlled by 
 namelist option.  Results are netcdf files that are then read into mom4.
 Various idealized options are available as selected by a namelist.
</DESCRIPTION><USE NAME="        fms_mod"/><USE NAME="mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="     mpp_io_mod"/><USE NAME="        mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="  constants_mod"/><NAMELIST NAME="idealized_bc_nml"><DATA NAME="wind_type" TYPE="character(len=128)">
  Control the iealized boundary wind stress condition options. 
  There are four options available and the default value is 
  "constant_tau". When temp_type is
  1. = "constant_tau", use space-time constant wind stress.
  2. = "cosine_zonal_winds", compute idealized winds using a cosine in latitude profile.  
        Makes sense only when running spherical coordinate model.
  3. = "frank_bryan_winds", compute idealized surface wind stress using zonal wind 
       profile originally  used by Frank Bryan. Makes sense only when running spherical coordinate model.
  4. = "frank_bryan_winds_compress", use the full Frank Bryan wind profiled over a 
        latitudinally compressed domain. Makes sense only when running spherical coordinate model. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="taux0" TYPE="real">
  Constant zonal wind stress 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="tauy0" TYPE="real">
  Constant meridional wind stress 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="qw0" UNITS="meter/sec" TYPE="real">
  Fresh water flux scaling parameter for idealized surface water flux 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="generate_wind_bc" TYPE="logical">
   Control if wind stress data will be generated. When true (default value), idealized surface boundary
   wind stress data will be generated. If false, do not generate wind stress data. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="generate_temp_bc" TYPE="logical">
   Control if temperature data will be generated. When true (default value), idealized surface boundary
   temperature data will be generated. If false, do not generate temperature data. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="generate_salt_bc" TYPE="logical">
   Control if salinity data will be generated. When true (default value), idealized surface boundary
   salinity data will be generated. If false, do not generate salinity data. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="generate_water_bc" TYPE="logical">
   Control if water flux data will be generated. When true (default value), idealized surface boundary
   water flux data will be generated. If false, do not generate water flux data. 
  </DATA></NAMELIST><SUBROUTINE NAME="idealized_bc_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialize the module generating ideal surface boundary conditions.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="idealized_bc_end" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
  Release memory.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="write_idealized_bc_data" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
    Write the idealized boundary condition to netcdf file.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
