<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_bihgen_friction_mod" DATE="2012/05/29 18:40:20" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/lateral"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> S. M. Griffies 
</CONTACT><OVERVIEW>
 This module computes thickness weighted and density weighted
 time tendency for horizontal velocity arising from 
 biharmonic friction. 
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 This module computes thickness weighted and density weighted
 time tendency for horizontal velocity arising from biharmonic
 friction. 

 The viscosity used to determine the strength of the tendency 
 can be a general function of space and time as specified by 
 the Smagorinsky approach as well as a grid-scale dependent
 background viscosity.  The form of the friction operator 
 can be isotropic or anisotropic in the lateral plane. 
</DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
 S.M. Griffies and R.W. Hallberg, 2000:
 Biharmonic friction with a Smagorinsky viscosity for use
 in large-scale eddy-permitting ocean models
 Monthly Weather Review, vol. 128, pages 2935-2946.
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 R.D. Smith and J.C. McWilliams, 2003:
 Anisotropic horizontal viscosity for ocean models,
 Ocean Modelling, vol. 5, pages 129-156. 
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Maltrud and Holloway, 2008: Implementing biharmonic neptune in a
 global eddying ocean model, Ocean Modelling, vol. 21, pages 22-34.
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Deremble, Hogg, Berloff, and Dewar, 2011:
 On the application of no-slip lateral boundary conditions to coarsely
 resolved ocean models, Ocean Modelling. 
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 S.M. Griffies, 2004: 
 Fundamentals of Ocean Climate Models 
 Princeton University Press
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
  Griffies, Elements of MOM (2012)
 </REFERENCE><NOTE>
 The ocean model can generally run with both Laplacian and biharmonic
 friction enabled at the same time.  Such has been found useful 
 for some eddying ocean simulations. 
 </NOTE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_bihgen_friction_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  Must be true to use this module. Default is false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging by printing checksums.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="k_smag_iso" UNITS="dimensionless" TYPE="real">
  This is the dimensionless Smagorinsky coefficient used to set the scale 
  of the Smagorinsky isotropic viscosity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="k_smag_aniso" UNITS="dimensionless" TYPE="real">
  This is the dimensionless Smagorinsky coefficient used to set the scale 
  of the Smagorinsky anisotropic viscosity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="vel_micom_iso" UNITS="m/sec" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM isotropic viscosity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="vel_micom_aniso" UNITS="m/sec" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM anisotropic viscosity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="visc_crit_scale" UNITS="dimensionless" TYPE="real">
  Scaling factor used to determine the critical viscosity, above which 
  the viscosity is not allowed to reach. 
  Use visc_crit_scale &lt; 1.0 for cases where the visc_crit from linear stability 
  allows for still too large of a viscosity.  Use visc_crit_scale&gt;1.0 when wish 
  to allow for larger viscosity. Default is visc_crit_scale=1.0.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="equatorial_zonal" TYPE="real">
  Orient the anisotropic friction within a latitudinal band according 
  to zonal direction. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="equatorial_zonal_lat" TYPE="real">
  Latitudinal band to use the zonal friction orientation. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="eq_vel_micom_iso" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM isotropic viscosity 
  within a user specified equatorial band. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="eq_vel_micom_aniso" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM anisotropic 
  viscosity within a user specified equatorial band. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="eq_lat_micom" TYPE="real">
  Equatorial latitude band (degrees) within which the MICOM viscosity
  is set according to eq_vel_micom_iso and eq_vel_micom_aniso.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="bottom_5point" TYPE="logical">
  To alleviate problems with small partial cells, it is often necessary
  to reduce the operator to the traditional 5-point Laplacian at the 
  ocean bottom.  This logical implements this mixing. 
  Default bottom_5point=.false. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="vel_micom_bottom" UNITS="m/sec" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM viscosity for 
  5point Laplacian at the bottom. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="ncar_boundary_scaling" TYPE="logical">
  To enhance the velocity scale used in western boundaries 
  for the isotropic and anisotropic  background viscosities, 
  we compute a scaling using the algorithm from the laplacian
  NCAR anisotropic scheme.
  Default ncar_boundary_scaling=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="ncar_boundary_scaling_read" TYPE="logical">
  To read in the ncar boundary scaling field rather than 
  generating it during initialization.  Generating during 
  initialization can be a bottle-neck on fine resolution models
  since there are some global 2d fields needed.  So if the 
  rescaling is produced once and then saved, it can be read
  in during subsequent runs without incurring the slowdown 
  of re-generating the scalings.  
  Default ncar_boundary_scaling_read=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="ncar_rescale_power" UNITS="dimensionless" TYPE="integer">
  For determining rescaling of the viscosity so to enhance the 
  friction near the western boundaries. Default ncar_rescale_power=1.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="ncar_vconst_4" UNITS="1/cm" TYPE="real">
  Inverse damping length for exponential falloff of the velocity scale 
  as move eastward away from western boundary. Default ncar_vconst_4=2.e-8.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="ncar_vconst_5" UNITS="dimensionless" TYPE="integer">
  For determining number of grid points in boundary calculation.
  Default ncar_vconst_5=3.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="neptune" TYPE="logical">
  Set to true for computing friction relative to Neptune barotropic velocity. 
  Default neptune=.false. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="neptune_length_eq" UNITS="m" TYPE="real">
  Length scale used to compute Neptune velocity at equator.  
  Default neptune_length_eq= 4.2e3 from Maltrud and Holloway.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="neptune_length_pole" UNITS="m" TYPE="real">
  Length scale used to compute Neptune velocity at pole. 
  Default neptune_length_pole= 17.0e3 from Maltrud and Holloway.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="neptune_depth_min" UNITS="m" TYPE="real">
  Minimum depth scale used for computing Neptune velocity.
  Default neptune_depth_min=100.0 from Maltrud and Holloway.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="neptune_smooth" TYPE="logical">
  For doing a horizontal 1-2-1 smoothing on the diagnosed  
  neptune velocity scale. 
  Default neptune_smooth=.true.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="neptune_smooth_num" TYPE="integer">
  Number of smoothing passes for neptune velocity.
  Default neptune_smooth_num=1.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="neptune_scaling" TYPE="real">
  Overall scaling parameter to help tune neptune.  
  Default neptune_scaling=1.0
  </DATA><DATA NAME="visc_diverge_scaling" TYPE="real">
  Dimensionless scaling used for divergence based viscosity.  
  Default visc_diverge_scaling=0.0 turns off the scheme. 
  visc_diverge_scaling=10.0 produces sensible viscosities for 
  1-degree model.  May need tuning for different resolutions.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="use_side_drag_friction" TYPE="logical">
  For converting friction at U-cells next to walls into 
  a drag law, as per Deremble et al. Use cdbot_array
  from ocean_core/ocean_bbc.F90 to compute drag force. 
  Default use_side_drag_friction=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="side_drag_friction_scaling" TYPE="real">
  Dimensionless scaling used for cdbot_array when setting
  side drag friction. So the effective side dragy coefficient
  is side_drag_friction_scaling*cdbot_array.  
  Default side_drag_friction_scaling=1.0.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="side_drag_friction_uvmag_max" UNITS="m/s" TYPE="real">
  Maximum magnitude of horizontal velocity used to compute the 
  side drag friction. This parameter can be useful especially
  for pressure models where the bottom cells can be quite thin 
  and subject to sporadic large magnitudes.  We do the same thing with 
  bottom drag calculations. 
  Default side_drag_friction_uvmag_max=10.0.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="side_drag_friction_max" UNITS="N/m^2" TYPE="real">
  Maximum magnitude of the side drag induced friction. 
  This parameter can be useful especially for pressure models 
  where the bottom cells can be quite thin and subject to sporadic
  large magnitudes.  We do the same thing with bottom drag calculations. 
  Default side_drag_friction_max=1.0.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="       constants_mod"/><USE NAME="    diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="             fms_mod"/><USE NAME="     mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="             mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="   ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_obc_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_operators_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="     ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="      ocean_util_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_bihgen_friction_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialize the horizontal biharmonic friction module by 
 registering fields for diagnostic output and performing some 
 numerical checks to see that viscosity is set appropriately.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="bihgen_friction" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 This subroutine computes the time tendency for horizontal 
 velocity (i.e., the acceleration) from horizontal biharmonic friction.  
 The algorithm is derived from a functional approach that ensures kinetic 
 energy is consistenty dissipated for all flow configurations. 
 The triad do-loops are expanded in order to enhance the 
 ability of cache-based machines to keep most of the variables 
 on-cache.  
 
 Fundamental to the scheme are the rates of horizontal deformation  <BR/>
 horizontal tension = DT = (dy)(u/dy)_x - (dx)(v/dx)_y              <BR/>
 horizontal strain  = DS = (dx)(u/dx)_y + (dy)(v/dy)_x              <BR/>
 Units of the tension and strain are sec^-1.

 Four tensions and four strains are computed for each velocity point, <BR/>
 corresponding to the four triads surrounding the point.              <BR/>
 The following notation is used to distinguish the triads:            <BR/>   
 (0,1)=northwest triad  (1,1)=northeast triad,                        <BR/> 
 (0,0)=southwest triad, (1,0)=southeast triad                        

 A triad contributes when at least one of its velocities is             
 not a land point.  In order to obtain the correct tension           
 and strain next to boundaries, tension and strain should not be       
 masked with umask. 

 As shown in Griffies and Hallberg (2000), 
 a biharmonic operator with a nonconstant viscosity is guaranteed to 
 dissipate kinetic energy *only* when using the sqrt of the biharmonic
 viscosity at each of the two stages of the algorithm. 
 The sqrt approach is employed here.  

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ncar_boundary_scale_read" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>

 Read in the 3d ncar boundary scaling field and use this to 
 rescale the background viscosities. 
 
 To use this routine, we need to already have generated the field
 ncar_rescale using the routine ncar_boundary_scale_create.

 The advantage of reading ncar_rescale is that we do not need to 
 introduce any global 2d arrays required for ncar_boundary_scale_create.     
 So the idea is to pay the price once by running ncar_boundary_scale_create,
 save ncar_rescale, then read that field in during subsequent runs through 
 ncar_boundary_scale_read.

 Here are the steps:
 1/ run one time with ncar_boundary_scaling_read=.false.
 and ncar_boundary_scaling=.true. 
 Be sure that the field ncar_rescale is saved in diagnostic table.
 To ensure answers agree whether reading ncar_rescale or creating it
 during initialization, it is necessary to save ncar_rescale using the
 double precision option in the diagnostic table (packing=1). 

 2/ extract field ncar_rescale from the diagnostics output
 and place into its own file INPUT/ncar_rescale.nc
 example extraction using ncks:
 ncks -v ncar_rescale 19900101.ocean_month.nc ncar_rescale.nc

 3/ set ncar_boundary_scaling_read=.true. 
 and ncar_boundary_scaling=.true., and now run the model 
 reading in ncar_rescale rather than regenerating
 it during each initialization (which can be a bottleneck 
 for large models on huge processor counts).   

 4/ As a check that all is fine, save ncar_rescale as a diagnostic
 for both the create and the read stage and make sure they agree.  
 Also, all checksums should agree whether reading in ncar_rescale
 or creating it each initialization, so long as the ncar_rescale.nc
 was saved with double precision  (see step 1/ above).

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ncar_boundary_scale_create" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>

     Recale the background viscosities to be larger in the western 
     boundary regions.  The algorithm is taken directly from the 
     anisotropic_ncar routine in ocean_lapgen_friction.F90.

   NOTE: The nearest western boundary computations are done along the
         model i-grid lines. Therefore, viscosity based on these are 
         only approximate in the high Northern Hemisphere when using 
         generalized coordinates with coordinate pole(s) shifted onto 
         land. 

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><FUNCTION NAME="BDX_EU_smag" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute backwards Derivative in X of a quantity defined on the east 
 face of a U-cell. Slightly modified version of BDX_EU used in
 ocean_operators.F90. If input is a(i,j) then output is defined 
 at (i-1/2,j).

 BDX_EU_smag changes dimensions by m^-3 

 </DESCRIPTION><IN NAME="a" TYPE="real" DIM="(isd:ied,jsd:jed)">
 field defined on the east face of a U-cell
 </IN></FUNCTION><FUNCTION NAME="BDY_NU_smag" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute backwards Derivative in Y of a quantity defined on the north
 face of a U-cell. Slightly modified version of BDY_EU used in
 ocean_operators.F90. If input is a(i,j) then output is defined 
 at (i,j-1/2).

 BDY_EU_smag changes dimensions by m^-3 

 </DESCRIPTION><IN NAME="a" TYPE="real" DIM="(isd:ied,jsd:jed)">
 field defined on the north face of a U-cell
 </IN></FUNCTION><SUBROUTINE NAME="bihgen_viscosity_check" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine to perform linear stability check for the biharmonic
 operator given a value for the horizontal biharmonic viscosity.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="bihgen_reynolds_check" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine to compute the biharmonic grid Reynolds number.  Large 
 Reynolds numbers indicate regions where solution may experience 
 some grid noise due to lack of enough horizontal friction. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="compute_neptune_velocity" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute Neptune velocity.  

 Method follows that of 
 Maltrud and Holloway, 2008: Implementing biharmonic neptune in a 
 global eddying ocean model, Ocean Modelling, vol. 21, pages 22-34. 

 March 2012
 Stephen.Griffies 

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
