<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_sigma_transport_mod" DATE="2012/05/17 13:41:45" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/lateral"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> Stephen M. Griffies
</CONTACT><OVERVIEW>
 Thickness weighted and density weighted time tendency for 
 tracer from transport within a bottom "sigma" layer.
 The advective portion of this routine is experimental,
 and has many problems.  It is retained in MOM for 
 exploratory use only.  Also note that the advection 
 contributes a lot of instability when running realistic
 simulations with pressure vertical coordinates. The 
 instability mechanism is unknown. 
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 This module computes the thickness weighted and density weighted
 time tendency for tracer arising from 

 1. Laplacian diffusion within a bottom turbulent boundary layer.

 2. Upwind advection within this layer.  Advection velocities 
    determined by model resolved velocity and parameterized 
    downslope velocity. We use first order upwind tracer advection
    to ensure positive definite tracer transport in the sigma 
    layer.  As the sigma layer is a proxy for a bottom turbulent
    boundary layer, the added mixing from the first order upwind
    should be physically acceptable.  

 CAUTION: The advective portion of this algorithm has problems
 and it retained in MOM only for research purposes.  It 
 is NOT supported for general use.  

 The diffusivity used to determine the strength of the diffusion  
 is generally set to be a function of the local horizontal grid 
 spacing.  Diffusivity is the sum of an a priori background plus
 a velocity dependent diffusivity.  It is large if there is a  
 a heavier parcel living adjacent within the "sigma layer" above
 a lighter parcel. It is small otherwise. 
 
 The advection is set to zero if the density is not downslope
 favorable.  That is, rho_{,x} * H_{,x} &lt; 0 for downslope
 flow in the x-direction, and likewise in the y-direction.  

 The thickness of the bottom layer can span more than a single 
 bottom grid cell.  This feature allows the sigma
 layer thickness to undulate in time according to the convergence
 or divergence of mass within the sigma layer. 

 </DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
 A. Beckmann and R. Doscher, 1997: A method for improved
 representation of dense water spreading over 
 topography in geopotential--coordinate models
 Journal of Physical Oceanography, vol 27, 
 pages 581--59.
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 R. Doscher and A. Beckmann, 2000:
 Effects of a bottom boundary layer parameterization 
 in a coarse-resolution model of the North Atlantic Ocean
 Journal of Atmospheric and Oceanic Technology, 
 vol 17 pages 698--707
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Campin and Goosse 1999: Parameterization of density-driven downsloping 
 flow for a coarse-resolution model in z-coordinate", Tellus 51A, 
 pages 412-430.
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 S.M. Griffies: Elements of MOM (2012)
 </REFERENCE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_sigma_transport_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  Must be true to use this module. Default is false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sigma_diffusion_on" TYPE="logical">
  For using sigma diffusion. Default is true.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sigma_advection_on" TYPE="logical">
  For using sigma advection. Default is false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sigma_advection_sgs_only" TYPE="logical">
  In many cases, adding the resolved transport to the 
  sigma-advective transport produces a tremendous level of 
  noise at the bottom.  The problem is that there are 
  grid-scale features that may cause large jumps in whether
  the velocity should be added or not, depending on the logic
  of the scheme.  For this reason, it may be prudent to remove
  the resolved velocity from that contributing to the sigma
  transport scheme. Note that its removal from sigma transport
  does not remove the contributions of the resolved velocity 
  from the resolved advective transport arising from
  ocean_tracer_advect_mod. It simply removes it from the 
  added transport arising in the sigma transport module. 
  Default is sigma_advection_sgs_only=.true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sigma_advection_check" TYPE="logical">
  If true, then will only include the resolved advection 
  velocity in the sigma-layer if the direction of 
  transport is downslope favorable for enhancing deep density.
  IF false, then will include the velocity regardless. 
  This option aims to reduce the large divergences
  that occur for the case when only include the velocity 
  if it is favorable for deep water getting more dense. 
  Default is sigma_advection_check=.true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="thickness_sigma_layer" UNITS="meter" TYPE="real">
  Initial thickness of the bottom sigma layer.   
  </DATA><DATA NAME="thickness_sigma_min" UNITS="meter" TYPE="real">
  Minimum thickness of the bottom sigma layer.   
  </DATA><DATA NAME="thickness_sigma_max" UNITS="meter" TYPE="real">
  Maximum thickness of the bottom sigma layer.   
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sigma_just_in_bottom_cell" TYPE="logical">
  For just having sigma layer in the bottom cell, as in mom4p0. 
  This option must be .false. in order to use sigma_advection_on=.true. 
  Default sigma_just_in_bottom_cell=.true.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="tmask_sigma_on" TYPE="logical">
  IF .true. then masks out fluxes passing into the sigma layer, except those 
  associated with sigma transport. Typically set to .false.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sigma_diffusivity" UNITS="m^2/sec" TYPE="real">
  Sigma tracer diffusivity for use if not using micom diffusivity.   
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sigma_diffusivity_ratio" UNITS="dimensionless" TYPE="real">
  When flow along sigma surface is stable (i.e., heavy parcels are below lighter parcels)
  then sigma diffusivity is reduced by sigma_diffusivity_ratio from the case where 
  heavy parcels are above lighter parcels.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="tracer_mix_micom" TYPE="logical">
  If .true., then the sigma diffusivity is set according to a velocity scale 
  times the grid spacing. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="vel_micom" UNITS="m/sec" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM diffusivity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="campingoose_mu" TYPE="real" UNITS="inverse seconds">
  Dissipation rate for the bottom friction.  Campin and Goosse 
  suggest campingoose_mu=10^-4
  </DATA><DATA NAME="campingoose_delta" TYPE="real" UNITS="dimensionless">
  Fraction of a grid cell participating in the overflow process. 
  Campin and Goosse suggest campingoose_delta=1/3. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sigma_umax" TYPE="real" UNITS="m/s">
  Maximum downslope speed allowed in sigma layer. 
  In some cases, the model will be unstable if sigma_umax
  is too large.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="smooth_sigma_velocity" TYPE="logical">
  To smooth the sigma advective transport velocity. 
  Default is smooth_sigma_velocity=.true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="smooth_sigma_thickness" TYPE="logical">
  To smooth the sigma thickness. This may be needed especially 
  for case with sigma advection, in which case the thickness 
  can become noisy. Default is smooth_sigma_thickness=.true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sigma_velmicom" TYPE="real" UNITS="m/s">
  For smoothing the sigma_thickness, use this as velocity scale to
  determine the thickness diffusivity.  
  Default is smooth_velmicom = 0.2
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="        constants_mod"/><USE NAME="     diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="              fms_mod"/><USE NAME="           fms_io_mod"/><USE NAME="      mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="              mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_density_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_operators_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_tracer_util_mod"/><USE NAME="      ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_util_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_sigma_transport_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialize the sigma transport module by registering fields for 
 diagnostic output and performing some numerical checks to see 
 that namelist settings are appropriate. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="sigma_transport" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 This subroutine computes the thickness weighted and density 
 weighted time tendency for tracer arising from transport in a 
 bottom turbulent boundary layer. The result is stored in 
 tracer th_tendency. 

 NOTE: In this algorithm, we ideally wish to have advection 
 velocity components on full data domain.  Unfortunately, 
 from ocean_advection_velocity_mod, they are only known 
 on the following domains:

 Adv_vel%uhrho_et: (isd,ied) x (jsc,jed)  
 Adv_vel%vhrho_nt: (isc,ied) x (jsd,jed).  

 So to proceed with the sigma_transport algorithm, we 
 transfer into local arrays and then update.  These 
 updates may be avoided (possibly), but at the price
 of much more logic in the algorithm.  We choose to 
 instead do the updates and have less logic.  This 
 decision may need to be revisited. 

 CAUTION: The advective portion of this algorithm 
 has fundamental problems.  It is retained in MOM
 only for process physics research purposes.  It is
 NOT recommended for use in general use. 
 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_sigma_transport_restart" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
  Write out restart files registered through register_restart_file
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_sigma_transport_end" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Write to restart.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="advect_sigma_upwind" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 First order upwind to advect tracers in sigma layer. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="watermass_diag_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialization of watermass diagnostic output files. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="watermass_diag" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Diagnose effects from sigma transport on the watermass transformation.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
