<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_lapcst_friction_mod" DATE="2012/06/01 20:47:08" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/lateral"><REVIEWER EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> Stephen M. Griffies
</REVIEWER><OVERVIEW>
 This module computes the thickness weighted and density weighted
 acceleration for horizontal velocity arising from horizontal 
 Laplacian friction. 
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 This module computes the thickness weighted and density weighted
 time tendency for horizontal velocity arising from horizontal
 Laplacian friction. 

 The viscosity used to determine the strength of the tendency 
 can be a general function of space yet it is constant in time.  
 A namelist option exists that determines this viscosity 
 as a local function of the grid spacing. 

</DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
  R. J. Murray and C. J. C. Reason,
  A curvilinear version of the Bryan-Cox ocean model
  Journal of Computational Physics (2002), vol 171, pages 1--46
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
  S.M. Griffies, Elements of MOM (2012)
 </REFERENCE><NOTE>
 The numerical implementation requires no calls to mpp_update_domains.  
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 This scheme has been found to be faster than the Smagorinsky viscosity 
 scheme.  However, the algorithm here is less robust since it 
 contains null modes in the terms associated with the sphericity 
 of the earth.  Hence, there may be flow configurations that are 
 not dissipated.
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 The sink from drag next to partial cells has been dropped 
 from MOM4p1.  
 </NOTE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_lapcst_friction_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  Must be true to use this module. Default is false. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging by printing checksums.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="alap" UNITS="m^2/sec" TYPE="real">
  This is the value for the space-time constant Laplacian viscosity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="velocity_mix_micom" TYPE="logical">
  If .true., then the viscosity is set according to a velocity scale times
  the cube of the grid spacing. It is based on an approach recommended by 
  Eric Chassignet that is used in the Miami Isopycnal Model.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="vel_micom" UNITS="m/sec" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM viscosity. 
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="       constants_mod"/><USE NAME="    diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="             fms_mod"/><USE NAME="     mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="             mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="   ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_obc_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_operators_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="     ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="      ocean_util_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_lapcst_friction_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialize the horizontal Laplacian friction module by 
 registering fields for diagnostic output and performing some 
 numerical checks to see that viscosity is set appropriately.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="lapcst_friction" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 This routine computes the rho*thickness weighted time tendency for
 horizontal velocity from horizontal Laplacian friction.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="lapcst_viscosity_check" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Perform linear stability check for the Laplacian operator 
 given a value for the horizontal laplacian viscosity.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="lapcst_reynolds_check" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine to compute the Laplacian grid Reynolds number.  Large 
 Reynolds numbers indicate regions where solution may experience 
 some grid noise due to lack of enough horizontal friction. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
