<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_mixdownslope_mod" DATE="2012/05/17 13:41:45" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/lateral"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> S.M. Griffies 
</CONTACT><OVERVIEW>
 Mixing of tracer between dense shallow parcel and 
 deeper parcels downslope. 
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 Mixing of tracer properties as dense shallow parcel is discharged
 into deeper water to approach the parcel's depth of neutral buoyancy.
 This module can be characterized as a mixture of the approach from
 Campin and Goosse (1999) and slope convection. 
</DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
 Campin and Goosse (1999): Parameterization of density-driven downsloping flow 
 for a coarse-resolution model in z-coordinate", Tellus 51A, pages 412-430
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 S.M. Griffies: Elements of MOM (2012)
 NOAA/Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory
 </REFERENCE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_mixdownslope_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For using this module.  Default use_this_module=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="do_bitwise_exact_sum" TYPE="logical">
  Set true to do bitwise exact global sum. When it is false, the global
  sum will be non-bitwise_exact, but will significantly increase efficiency. 
  The default value is false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="mixdownslope_npts" TYPE="integer">
  Number of horizontally distant points used in search downslope. 
  Note: it is not possible to have 
  mixdownslope_npts greater than or equal to the computational domain
  extents, as this would require updates across multiple processors. 
  Default mixdownslope_npts=1. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="mixdownslope_frac_central" TYPE="real">
  Fraction of the central cell that participates in downslope mixing
  in any particular direction.  Default mixdownslope_frac_central=0.25
  </DATA><DATA NAME="mixdownslope_weight_far" TYPE="logical">
  To place more weight on points further from central point.  This may 
  be done to enhance properties getting downslope.  Default is 
  mixdownslope_weight_far=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="mixdownslope_width" TYPE="integer">
  Width of the re-weighting function used to emphasize points further 
  along in the search for exchange points.  Default mixdownslope_width=1.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="read_mixdownslope_mask" TYPE="logical">
  For reading in a mask that selects regions of the domain 
  where mixdownslope is allowed to function (mask=1) or not 
  to function (mask=0). Default read_mixdownslope_mask=.false., 
  whereby mixdownslope_mask is set to tmask(k=1). 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="mixdownslope_mask_gfdl" TYPE="logical">
  For modifying the mixdownslope mask based on reading in 
  the GFDL regional mask. Default mixdownslope_mask_gfdl=.false.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="        constants_mod"/><USE NAME="     diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="              fms_mod"/><USE NAME="      mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="              mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_density_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_tracer_util_mod"/><USE NAME="      ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_util_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_mixdownslope_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initial set up for mixing of tracers into the abyss next to topography.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="mixdownslope" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute thickness and density weighted tracer tendency [tracer*rho*m/s]
 due to exchange of tracer properties in regions where density-driven
 downslope transport is favorable. 

 Allow for exchanges to occur over horizontally 
 distant points, so long as the dense shallow parcel finds that it 
 will sit on the bottom of the horizontally adjacent columns.  Doing
 so requires a search algorithm, which requires some if-test logic
 as well as extended halos.  Note that the halos cannot be extended
 to larger than the size of the computational domain on a processor.
 This restriction limits the extent that we can search horizontally.

 The rates for the exchange are functions of the topographic slope
 and the density differences between parcels.  

 This scheme can be characterized as a slope convection based on 
 logic incorporated into the overflow and overexchange schemes. 

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="watermass_diag_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialization of watermass diagnostic output files. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="watermass_diag" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Diagnose effects from mixdownslope on the watermass transformation.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
