<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_lap_friction_mod" DATE="2012/07/10 03:45:18" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/lateral"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> Stephen M. Griffies
</CONTACT><OVERVIEW>
 This module calls the appropriate lateral laplacian friction modules. 
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 This module serves as an interface to the chosen lateral 
 laplacian friction modules.  
</DESCRIPTION><INFO><NOTE>
 The model can generally run with both Laplacian and biharmonic friction
 enabled at the same time.  Such has been found useful for some eddying 
 ocean simulations. 
 </NOTE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_lap_friction_nml"><DATA NAME="lap_friction_scheme" TYPE="character">
 To determine the laplacian friction scheme: "const" or "general"
 </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="write_a_restart" TYPE="logical">
  Set true to write a restart.  False setting only for rare 
  cases where wish to benchmark model without measuring the cost
  of writing restarts and associated chksums.  
  Default is write_a_restart=.true. 
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="           diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="                    fms_mod"/><USE NAME="                 fms_io_mod"/><USE NAME="            mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="                    mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="          ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_lapcst_friction_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_lapgen_friction_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_lapcgrid_friction_mod"/><USE NAME="        ocean_operators_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="            ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="             ocean_util_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_lap_friction_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialize the horizontal Laplacian friction module.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="lap_friction" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute the thickness weighted and density weighted accel due to 
 lateral laplacian friction.  Add this contribution to Velocity%accel. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="lap_viscosity_check" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 To check that the viscosity is not too large. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="lap_reynolds_check" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 To check that the Reynolds number is not too large. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="lap_friction_barotropic" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>

 This routine computes the laplacian friction acting on a two-dim
 array.  It uses the two-dimensional vertically averaged viscosity 
 used in the laplacian friction module.  The intent is to apply this
 2d operator to the vertically integrated horizontal momentum. We 
 ignore the spherical metric terms in this form of the operator, 
 since we are aiming for a fast smoothing operator to be applied
 during each of the many barotropic time steps.  We also apply 
 just the isotropic portion of the more general anisotropic 
 laplacian operator.  

 This scheme is only meant for the B-grid version of MOM.  It 
 has not been generalized to the C-grid, since the C-grid has 
 less noise in the barotropic gravity waves anyhow, so it is 
 unlikely there will need to be extra friction applied to the 
 C-grid barotropic equations.

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_lap_friction_restart" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
  Write out restart files registered through register_restart_file
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_lap_friction_end" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Write to restart of the vertically averaged viscosity. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
