<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_bihcst_friction_mod" DATE="2012/06/08 20:15:35" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/lateral"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> Stephen M. Griffies
</CONTACT><OVERVIEW>
 Thickness weighted and density weighted time tendency for velocity
 from horizontal biharmonic friction 
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 This module computes the thickness and density weighted time tendency
 for horizontal velocity arising from horizontal biharmonic friction. 
 The viscosity used to determine the strength of the tendency 
 can be a general function of space yet it is constant in time.  
 A namelist option exists that determines this viscosity 
 as a local function of the grid spacing. 
</DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
  R. J. Murray and C.J.C. Reason,
  A curvilinear version of the Bryan-Cox ocean model
  Journal Computational Physics (2002), vol 171, pages 1-46
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
  Elements of MOM (2012), S.M. Griffies 
 </REFERENCE><NOTE>
 The numerical implementation requires one call to mpp_update_domains if 
 running the model with halo=1.  
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 This scheme has been found to be faster than the Smagorinsky viscosity 
 scheme.  However, the algorithm here is less robust since it 
 contains null modes in the terms associated with the sphericity 
 of the earth.  Hence, there may be flow configurations that are 
 not dissipated.
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 The model can generally run with both Laplacian and biharmonic friction
 enabled at the same time. Such has been found useful for some eddying 
 ocean simulations. 
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 The numerical implementation in mom4p1 and mom5 does not include the sink due 
 to partial bottom cells. This sink was implemented in mom2 and mom3
 and mom4.  It is not known how relevant this sink is.  
 </NOTE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_bihcst_friction_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  Must be true to use this module.  Default is false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging by printing checksums.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="abih" UNITS="m^4/sec" TYPE="real">
  This is the value for the space-time constant biharmonic viscosity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="velocity_mix_micom" TYPE="logical">
  If .true., then the viscosity is set according to a velocity scale times
  the cube of the grid spacing. It is based on an approach recommended by 
  Eric Chassignet that is used in the Miami Isopycnal Model.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="vel_micom" UNITS="m/sec" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM viscosity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="eq_vel_micom" UNITS="m/sec" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM viscosity within a latitude
  band surrounding the equator.  This is useful for some models of enhanced equatorial
  resolution that can maintain numerical integrity in this region with less friction 
  than outside the tropical band.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="eq_lat_micom" TYPE="real">
  Equatorial latitude band (degrees) within which the MICOM viscosity is set according 
  to eq_vel_micom.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="       constants_mod"/><USE NAME="    diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="             fms_mod"/><USE NAME="     mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="             mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="   ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_obc_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_operators_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="     ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="      ocean_util_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_bihcst_friction_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialize the horizontal biharmonic friction module by 
 registering fields for diagnostic output and performing some 
 numerical checks to see that viscosity is set appropriately.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="bihcst_friction" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 This subroutine computes the thickness weighted acceleration on
 horizontal velocity arising from horizontal biharmonic friction.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="delsq_velocity" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the laplacian operator acting on velocity.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="bihcst_viscosity_check" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine to perform linear stability check for the biharmonic
 operator given a value for the horizontal biharmonic viscosity.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="bihcst_reynolds_check" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine to compute the biharmonic grid Reynolds number.  Large 
 Reynolds numbers indicate regions where solution may experience 
 some grid noise due to lack of enough horizontal friction. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
