<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_bih_tracer_mod" DATE="2012/06/01 20:47:08" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/lateral"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> Stephen M. Griffies
</CONTACT><OVERVIEW>
 Thickness weighted and density weighted time tendency
 for tracer from biharmonic tracer mixing. 
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 There are two main options for computing the fluxes.

 (1) The lateral fluxes can be aligned with the z-coordinate surfaces,
 in which case the fluxes must be approximated if (i) we use non-geopotential
 vertical coordinates, (ii) next to partial bottom step topography.
 This form of the diffusion is not recommended since it can lead to 
 the creation of spurious extrema.  

 (2) The lateral fluxes can be aligned surfaces of constant vertical 
 coordinate. In this case the fluxes are no longer strictly "horizontal."
 Howerver, the operator is simpler and it ensures that no suprious
 extrema are created. It is for this reason that the simpler operator
 is preferred.   
  
 The diffusivity used to determine the strength of the tendency can be 
 a general function of space yet it is constant in time.  A namelist 
 option exists that determines this diffusivity as a local function 
 of the grid spacing. 
</DESCRIPTION><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_bih_tracer_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  Must be true to use this module
  </DATA><DATA NAME="horz_z_diffuse" TYPE="logical">
  To compute fluxes along surfaces of constant depth.
  This operation must necessarily be approximate for the two 
  cases (i) non-geopotential vertical coordinates, (2)
  next to partial bottom step topography.  There are cases where
  use of this operator can lead to spurious creation of extrema
  due to truncation errors associated with the "slope" term.
  The option to use horz_z_diffuse=.true. is maintained for 
  legacy purposes alone.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="horz_s_diffuse" TYPE="logical">
  To compute diffusion along surfaces of constant vertical s-coordinate. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="abih" UNITS="m^4/sec" TYPE="real">
  This is the value for the space-time constant biharmonic diffusivity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="tracer_mix_micom" TYPE="logical">
  If .true., then the diffusivity is set according to a velocity scale times
  the cube of the grid spacing. It is based on an approach recommended by 
  Eric Chassignet that is used in the Miami Isopycnal Model.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="vel_micom" UNITS="m/sec" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM diffusivity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="read_diffusivity_mask" TYPE="logical">
  Allows for reading of a mask that to apply diffusivity
  only in selected regions.  
  Default read_diffusivity_mask=.false. 
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="       constants_mod"/><USE NAME="    diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="             fms_mod"/><USE NAME="     mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="             mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="   ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_operators_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_obc_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="     ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_bih_tracer_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialize the biharmonic tracer mixing module by 
 registering fields for diagnostic output and performing some 
 numerical checks to see that diffusivity is set appropriately.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="bih_tracer" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 This function computes the thickness weighted and density weighted
 time tendency for tracer from biharmonic mixing. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="delsq_tracer" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the laplacian operator acting on tracer with unit 
 diffusivity. Units of del2_tracer are tracer/length^2
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
