<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_xlandinsert_mod" DATE="2012/05/15 16:05:39" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/sources"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> S.M. Griffies 
</CONTACT><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> K.W. Dixon
</CONTACT><REVIEWER EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> M.J. Harrison
</REVIEWER><OVERVIEW>
 Tracer and mass source from cross-land insertion.
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute thickness and density weighted tendency [rho*tracer*meter/sec]
 of tracer associated with cross-land insertion.  Also compute 
 mass source from cross-land insertion.  
</DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
 S.M. Griffies, M.J. Harrison, R. C. Pacanowski, and A. Rosati
 A Technical Guide to MOM4 (2003)
 NOAA/Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory
 </REFERENCE><NOTE>
 Algorithm ensures both total tracer and total mass is conserved.
 Algorithm sets up the insertion points as in xlandmix, and 
 transports between the columns as in rivermix. 
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 2D domain decomposition is implemented according to following
 notions.  If the two points in an xlandinsert pair live within halo 
 of each other (i.e., within same local_domain), 
 then no added mpp communication required. However, nore generally 
 the two points live further away.  In this case, xland_domain
 is defined so that its halos incorporate the maximum separation 
 of xlandinsert points.  New tracer, eta, and grid arrays
 are defined over this extended xland_domain.  This added domain
 size will come at some computational cost, so it is advantageous
 to limit the separation between points within an xlandinsert pair. 
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 The current implementation of xlandinsert has not been generalized 
 to allow for communication between points separated by the tripolar fold.  
 The problem is in the logic used to compute xland_domain.  
 There is nothing fundamental limiting a generalization of the
 logic used to generate xland_domain.
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 Many of the user specified values given in USER INPUT are
 model dependent since unresolved straits can become resolved 
 in finer mesh models. 
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 BUG FIX 30 May 2011. 
 Trying to mix across the ends of the global domain results in incorrect indexing.
 Local indices need to be incremented/decremented by the global extent.
 Russell.Fiedler@csiro.au
 </NOTE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_xlandinsert_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  Needs to be true in order to use this scheme. Default is false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="verbose_init" TYPE="logical">
  For verbose initialization information.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="        constants_mod"/><USE NAME="     diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="    field_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="              fms_mod"/><USE NAME="      mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="              mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_tracer_util_mod"/><USE NAME="      ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_xlandinsert_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
    Initial set up for crossland insertion of tracers and eta 

    Checks are performed to ensure that the crossland mixing
    grid locations are valid according to model configuration.

    A summary of the locations of crossland points is written out.

    User specified inputs in "USER INPUT" section:

    ixland and jxland = user specified nxland pairs of i,j grid locations

    kxland = user specified uppermost (ktop=kxland(n,1)) and  
             deepest (kbot=kxland(n,2)) levels over which crossland 
             will be done for each crossland pair. Note the for 
             xlandinsert, kxland(nxl,1)=1 is required, since the 
             aim is to move excess volume from one column to another. 

    tauxland = user specified time constant (seconds) setting the rate 
               of transport via upwind advection.  

    NOTE: for ixland, jxland, and kxland pairs, values of the
    (n,1) element should be &lt; the corresponding (n,2) value.

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="xlandinsert" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute thickness and density weighted tracer source 
 [(kg/m^3)*tracer*m/s] and mass source (kg/m^3)*(m/s)
 associated with discharge of tracer from surface of a 
 thick column into a set of boxes within a thin column. 

 NOTE:
 Compute rho_dzt_x as if using a geopotential model, since the  
 xlandinsert rates are typically first tuned with geopotential models.
 also, we wish to have the transport proportional to differences in 
 eta_t, which for zstar and pstar are generally must larger than 
 differences in dzt.  

 Modified by Keith.Dixon (January 2004) 

 Modified by Stephen.Griffies for general 
 vertical coordinates January 2005 and August 2006.

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="xlandinsert_mass" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute the mass source (kg/m^3)*meter/sec. 

 Note that xlandinsert has already been called, so xland_rho_dzt 
 has been filled.  
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><FUNCTION NAME="at_least_one_in_comp_domain" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Function to see if at least one of the two points in a crossland pair
 is within the computational domain for the processor. 
 </DESCRIPTION><IN NAME="nxl" TYPE="integer">
 Integer labeling the particular xlandinsert pair
 </IN></FUNCTION><FUNCTION NAME="on_comp_domain" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Determine if the point is in comp-domain for the processor
 </DESCRIPTION><IN NAME="nxl" TYPE="integer">
 Integer labeling the particular xlandinsert pair
 </IN><IN NAME="lx" TYPE="integer">
 lx=1,2 labels the point within an xlandinsert pair
 </IN></FUNCTION><FUNCTION NAME="on_processor" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Determine if the point is on processor
 </DESCRIPTION></FUNCTION><SUBROUTINE NAME="watermass_diag_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialization of watermass diagnostic output files. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="watermass_diag" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Diagnose effects from xlandinsert on watermass transformation.  
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
