<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_sponges_velocity_mod" DATE="2012/05/17 13:41:49" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/sources"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov.au"> Paul Sandery
</CONTACT><OVERVIEW>
 Thickness weighted velocity tendency [meter*meter/sec*sec] from sponges.
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>

 This module applies sponges to currents. The sponges
 can occur at any location and with any distribution in the domain, and
 with any time step and damping rate.  Sponges occur where positive
 inverse restore times occur in the field passed to sponge_init.  An
 array of tracer tendencies due to the sponges is augmented through a
 call to sponge_tracer_source.  The array of tracer tendencies must be
 reset to zero between calls.

 Different damping rates can be specified for each field by making
 calls to register_sponge_rate - no sponges are applied to fields for
 which uniformly zero inverse damping rates are set with a call to
 register_sponge_rate.  The value towards which a field is damped is
 set with calls to register_sponge_field; successive calls are used to
 set up linear interpolation of this restore rate.

 Sponge data and damping coefficients are generally 3 dimensional. 

 The user is responsible for providing (and registering) the data on
 the model grid of values towards which the currents are being driven.

</DESCRIPTION><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_sponges_velocity_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For using this module.  Default use_this_module=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="damp_coeff_3d" TYPE="logical">
  For case when damping coefficients are full 3d field of values.
  Default damp_coeff_3d=.false., which means damping coeffs are 
  2d horizontal array.   
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="        diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="                 fms_mod"/><USE NAME="                 mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="time_interp_external_mod"/><USE NAME="        time_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="         ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="     ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_sponges_velocity_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 This subroutine is intended to be used to initialize the sponges.
 Everything in this subroutine is a user prototype, and should be replacable.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="sponge_velocity_source" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 This subroutine calculates thickness weighted and density weighted
 time tendencies due to damping by sponges.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
