<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_shortwave_jerlov_mod" DATE="2012/05/17 13:41:49" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/sources"><CONTACT EMAIL="martin.schmidt@io-warnemuende.de"> Martin Schmidt
</CONTACT><REVIEWER EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> S.M. Griffies 
</REVIEWER><OVERVIEW>
 This module returns thickness and density weighted temperature 
 tendency [kg/m^3 * deg C *m/sec] from penetrative shortwave heating.
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute thickness and density weighted tendency [deg C *m/sec *kg/m^3]
 of temperature associated with penetrative shortwave heating in the upper
 ocean. 

 This module ussumes a simple double exponential decay law. The e-folding 
 depth may vary spatially and temporaly.  

 The exponentials represents a parameterization of the
 attenuation coefficient for light between 300 um and 750 um in the following
 form:

      E(z) = E(0) * (r1*exp(-z/efold1) + (1-r1)*exp(-z/efold2))
      with z &gt; 0 the ocean depth 

 The "efold" is the efolding depth of the long and short
 visable and ultra violet light.
 efold will vary between 30 m in oligotrophic waters and 4 m in coastal
 regions. 

 If the thickness of the first ocean level "dzt(1)" is 50 meters,
 then shortwave penetration does not do much. However, for finer 
 vertical resolution, such as dzt(1) = 10 meters commonly used
 in ocean climate models, the effect of shortwave heating can
 be significant. This can be particularly noticable in the summer
 hemisphere.

 Radiation at the bottom is set to zero, hence the remaining radiation
 at the bottom of the deepest ocean cells is totally absorbed 
 by these cells. This implies, that partial cells need not to
 be considered explicitly. Radiation at tracer depth within these 
 cells is not set to zero. This differs from 
 ocean_shortwave_gfdl and ocean_shortwave_csiro and reduces slightly the
 bouyancy forcing to the mixing layer in the kpp-scheme, if surface mixing 
 goes down to the bottom. 
 
 </DESCRIPTION><INFO><NOTE>
  The efolding depth is depth independent.
 </NOTE><NOTE>
  Simpson and Dickey (1981) and others have argued between one and 
  two exponentials for light between 300 um and 750 um.  
  With vertical grid resolution of 5 meters or finer
  for the upper 20 meters, a second exponential will make a difference.
 </NOTE><REFERENCE>
 Jerlov (1968)
 Optical Oceanography
 Elsevier Press
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Paulson and Simpson (1977)
 Irradiance measurements in the upper ocean
 Journal of Physical Oceanography vol 7 pages 952-956
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Rosati and Miyakoda (1988)
 A General Circulation Model for Upper Ocean Simulation
 Journal of Physical Oceanography vol 18 pages 1601-1626.
 </REFERENCE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_shortwave_jerlov_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module=" TYPE="logical">
   Must be .true. to run with module. Default is false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sw_frac_top" TYPE="real">
   The fraction of shortwave radiation that should be incorporated into 
   the sw_source array at k=1.  The generic treatment in MOM is to assume
   that shortwave radiation is already contained inside the 
   T_prog(index_temp)%stf field. Hence, to avoid   
   double counting, sw_frac(k=0)=sw_frac_top should=0.0.
   If one removes shortwave from stf, then set sw_frac_top=1.0.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="f_vis_in" TYPE="real">
   F_vis is the amount of light in the shortwave versus the long wave.
   F_vis=0.54 on sunny days and F_vis=0.60 on cloudy days. With 
   override_f_vis  = .true. F_vis is defined from f_vis_in.
   We believe, that this effect is in the first exponential in 
   Paulson and Simpson (1977). The default is f_vis_in=1., instead of .57
   but it is still possible to define this quantity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="rpart_in" TYPE="real">
   rpart_in = (0..1)   
  </DATA><DATA NAME="coef1_in" UNITS="meter" TYPE="real">
  </DATA><DATA NAME="coef2_in" UNITS="meter" TYPE="real">
  </DATA><DATA NAME="override_coeff" TYPE="logical">
   With override_coeff  = .true. rpart_in, coef1_in, coef2_in specify
   the parameters for the double exponential. The default is .false..
  </DATA><DATA NAME="override_f_vis" TYPE="logical">
   With override_f_vis  = .true. F_vis is defined from f_vis_in,
   otherwise it is the shortwave versus the long wave amount of light.
   The default is .true.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="zmax_pen" UNITS="meter" TYPE="real">
   Maximum depth of penetration of shortwave radiation. 
   Below this depth, shortwave penetration is exponentially 
   small and so is ignored.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="baltic_optics, jerlov_1, jerlov_2, jerlov_3, jerlov_1a, jerlov_1b" TYPE="logical">
   Logical switch to select a watertype. Default=.false.. The model stops, if none is selected
   and override_coeff=.false..  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="enforce_sw_frac" TYPE="logical">
  To ensure the shortwave fraction is monotonically decreasing with depth. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sw_pen_fixed_depths" TYPE="logical">
  To compute penetration assuming fixed depths via Grd%zw(k) depths.
  This is strictly incorrect when have undulating free surface or 
  generatlized vertical coordinates.  This option is here for purposes
  of legacy, as this was done in MOM4.0 versions. It saves some compute time
  if the surface elevation is small compared with the upper cells' thickness.
  The default is .false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging purposes.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="           constants_mod"/><USE NAME="                 fms_mod"/><USE NAME="                 mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="time_interp_external_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="         ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="     ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_shortwave_jerlov_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialization for the shortwave module
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="sw_source_jerlov" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Add short wave penetrative heating to T_prog(index_temp)%th_tendency.

 Note that the divergence of shortwave for the first
 level "div_sw(0)" is compensating for the effect of having
 the shortwave component already included in the total
 surface tracer flux "stf(i,j,temp)"

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
