<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_shortwave_csiro_mod" DATE="2012/05/17 13:41:49" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/sources"><CONTACT EMAIL="Russell.Fiedler@csiro.au"> Russell Fiedler 
</CONTACT><REVIEWER EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> S.M. Griffies 
</REVIEWER><REVIEWER EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> Alexander Pletzer
</REVIEWER><OVERVIEW>
 This module returns thickness and density weighted temperature 
 tendency [kg/m^3 * deg C *m/sec] from penetrative shortwave heating.
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute thickness and density weighted tendency [deg C *m/sec *kg/m^3]
 of temperature associated with penetrative shortwave heating in the upper
 ocean. Generally penetration is taken as a function of monthly optical 
 properties of the upper ocean, where optical properties are read 
 in from a file of climatological data.

 This module ussumes a simple single exponential decay law. The e-folding 
 depth may vary spatially and temporaly.  This routine is commonly 
 used by researchers at CSIRO Marine and Atmospheric Research in 
 Australia.  It has been optimized for vector peformance in 
 June 2003 on the Australian NEC computer. 
 </DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
 Jerlov (1968)
 Optical Oceanography
 Elsevier Press
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Morel and Antoine (1994)
 Heating rate in the upper ocean in relation to its bio-optical state 
 Journal of Physical Oceanography vol 24 pages 1652-1664
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Paulson and Simpson (1977)
 Irradiance measurements in the upper ocean
 Journal of Physical Oceanography vol 7 pages 952-956
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Rosati and Miyakoda (1988)
 A General Circulation Model for Upper Ocean Simulation
 Journal of Physical Oceanography vol 18 pages 1601-1626.
 </REFERENCE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_shortwave_csiro_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module=" TYPE="logical">
  Must be .true. to run with module. Default is false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="read_depth" TYPE="logical">
  If .true. then read in e folding depth for radiation attenuation. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sw_frac_top" TYPE="real">
  The fraction of shortwave radiation that should be incorporated into 
  the sw_source array at k=1.  The generic treatment in MOM is to assume
  that shortwave radiation is already contained inside the 
  T_prog(index_temp)%stf field. Hence, to avoid   
  double counting, sw_frac(k=0)=sw_frac_top should=0.0.
  If one removes shortwave from stf, then set sw_frac_top=1.0.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="zmax_pen" UNITS="meter" TYPE="real">
   Maximum depth of penetration of shortwave radiation. 
   Below this depth, shortwave penetration is exponentially 
   small and so is ignored.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="depth_default" UNITS="mg/m^3" TYPE="real">
   Default efolding depth = 20m.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="enforce_sw_frac" TYPE="logical">
  To ensure the shortwave fraction is monotonically decreasing with depth. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sw_pen_fixed_depths" TYPE="logical">
  To compute penetration assuming fixed depths via Grd%zw(k) depths.
  This is strictly incorrect when have undulating free surface or 
  generatlized vertical coordinates.  This option is here for purposes
  of legacy, as this was done in MOM4.0 versions. The default is .false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging purposes.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="          axis_utils_mod"/><USE NAME="       field_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="                 fms_mod"/><USE NAME="                 mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="time_interp_external_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="         ocean_types_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_shortwave_csiro_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialization for the shortwave module
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="sw_source_csiro" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Add short wave penetrative heating to T_prog(index_temp)%th_tendency.

 Note that the divergence of shortwave for the first
 level "div_sw(0)" is compensating for the effect of having
 the shortwave component already included in the total
 surface tracer flux "stf(i,j,temp)"

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="sw_pen" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
  Absorbtion of shortwave radiation in the water assumes energy partitions
  represented by a single exponential:

  The exponentialsrepresents a parameterization of the
  attenuation coefficient for light between 300 um and 750 um in the following
  form:

	E(z) = E(0) * exp(z/efold))
       with z &lt; 0 the ocean depth 

  The "efold" s the efolding depth of the long and short
  visable and ultra violet light.
  efold will vary between 30 m in oligotrophic waters and 4 m in coastal
  regions. 

  If the thickness of the first ocean level "dzt(1)" is 50 meters,
  then shortwave penetration does not do much. However, for finer 
  vertical resolution, such as dzt(1) = 10 meters commonly used
  in ocean climate models, the effect of shortwave heating can
  be significant. This can be particularly noticable in the summer
  hemisphere.

 </DESCRIPTION><INFO><NOTE>
  The terms contributing to sw_fk(i,j) are depth independent
 </NOTE><NOTE>
  Simpson and Dickey (1981) and others have argued between one and 
  two exponentials for light between 300 um and 750 um.  
  With vertical grid resolution of 5 meters or finer
  for the upper 20 meters, a second exponential will make a difference.
 </NOTE></INFO></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
