<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_xlandmix_mod" DATE="2012/05/17 13:41:49" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/sources"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> S.M. Griffies 
</CONTACT><REVIEWER EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> M.J. Harrison 
</REVIEWER><REVIEWER EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> K. Dixon 
</REVIEWER><OVERVIEW>
 Tracer and mass source from cross-land mixing.
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute thickness weighted and density weighted tendency
 [tracer*(kg/m^3)*meter/sec] of tracer and mass associated with 
 cross-land mixing of points. 

 In particular, this module provides interaction between bodies of
 water separated by land in coarse models (e.g., Med-Atlantic).  
 Interaction consists of mixing tracer and mass between water 
 columns found on each side of the land barrier.

 To conserve total tracer when using xlandmix with k=1, 
 also need to connect mass between remote bodies of water
 via xlandmix of eta.  

 When connecting cells with k&gt;1, we do not mix mass. This 
 is ensured by making the time tendency only a function of the 
 difference in tracer concentration. 

</DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
 S.M. Griffies, M.J. Harrison, R. C. Pacanowski, and A. Rosati
 A Technical Guide to MOM4 (2004)
 NOAA/Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 S.M. Griffies: Elements of MOM (2012)
 NOAA/Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory
 </REFERENCE><NOTE>
 Algorithm ensures both total tracer and total mass is conserved.
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 2D domain decomposition is implemented according to following
 notions.  If the two points in an xlandmix pair live within halo 
 of each other (i.e., within same local_domain), 
 then no added mpp communication required. However, more generally 
 the two points live further away.  In this case, xland_domain
 is defined so that its halos incorporate the maximum separation 
 of xlandmix points.  New tracer, eta, and grid arrays
 are defined over this extended xland_domain.  This added domain
 size will come at some computational cost, so it is advantageous
 to limit the separation between points within an xlandmix pair. 
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 The current implementation of xlandmix has not been generalized 
 to allow for communication between points separated by the tripolar fold.  
 The problem is in the logic used to compute xland_domain.  
 There is nothing fundamental limiting a generalization of the
 logic used to generate xland_domain.
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 Many of the user specified values given in USER INPUT are
 model dependent since unresolved straits can become resolved 
 in finer mesh models. 
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 Algorithm originally developed by Keith Dixon (Keith.Dixon) 
 for rigid lid and full cells and one processor (i.e., MOM1).  
 Algorithm extended to free surface and partial cells and 2D 
 domain decomposition by S.M.Griffies (Stephen.Griffies).
 Further extensions to generalized vertical coordinates by 
 Stephen.Griffies
 </NOTE><NOTE>
 BUG FIX 30 May 2011. 
 Trying to mix across the ends of the global domain results in incorrect indexing.
 Local indices need to be incremented/decremented by the global extent.
 Russell.Fiedler@csiro.au
 </NOTE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_xlandmix_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  Needs to be true in order to use this scheme. Default is false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="xlandmix_kmt" TYPE="logical">
  To allow xlandmixing to occur at k=kmt cell.  
  Default is xlandmix_kmt=.false. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="verbose_init" TYPE="logical">
  For verbose initialization information.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="        constants_mod"/><USE NAME="     diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="    field_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="              fms_mod"/><USE NAME="      mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="              mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_tracer_util_mod"/><USE NAME="      ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_xlandmix_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
    Initial set up for crossland mixing of tracers 

    (i,j,k) locations of crossland mixing points are set via 
    field table entries.

    Time invariant crossland mixing rates (in units of m**3/sec) are 
    set via field table entries. 

    Checks are performed to ensure that the crossland mixing
    grid locations are valid according to model configuration.

    A summary of the locations of crossland mixing points is written out.

    User specified inputs in "USER INPUT" section:

    ixland and jxland = user specified nxland pairs of i,j grid locations

    kxland = user specified uppermost (ktop=kxland(n,1)) and deepest 
             (kbot=kxland(n,2)) levels over which crossland mixing will 
             be done for each pair of crossland mixing points.

    vxland = user specified time invariant rates of crossland mixing (m3/sec)
             Equivalent to "the flow to the east = the flow to the west"
             Dynamic vxland is not available in MOM. 

    NOTE: for ixland, jxland, and kxland pairs, values of the
    (n,1) element should be &lt; the corresponding (n,2) value.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="xlandmix" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute thickness and density weighted time tendency from 
 xlandmix. Units of the tendency are tracer*(kg/m^3)*meter/sec.

 Logic is a bit tricky in order to allow each (i,j,k) point
 to participate in an arbitrary number of xlandmix pairs.  

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="xlandmix_mass" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute the mass source kg/(m^2*sec).
 Note that xlandmix has already been called, so xland_mass has been 
 filled.  
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="xland_check" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Check if prescribed too much mixing

 In this routine the crossland mixing rate vxland(nxl) for
 the pair of points associated with index number nxl is
 converted into the fraction of the model grid boxes to be mixed
 per second, and checked.  These checks ensure that the rate of
 crossland mixing requested is valid in that it can be realized
 given the timestep length and column volumes involved.
 </DESCRIPTION><IN NAME="nxl" TYPE="integer">
 Integer labeling the particular xlandmix pair
 </IN><INOUT NAME="error" TYPE="logical">
 Error flag indicates whether initialization was performed successfully.  
 </INOUT></SUBROUTINE><FUNCTION NAME="at_least_one_in_comp_domain" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Function to see if at least one of the two points in a crossland pair
 is within the computational domain for the processor. 
 </DESCRIPTION><IN NAME="nxl" TYPE="integer">
 Integer labeling the particular xlandmix pair
 </IN></FUNCTION><FUNCTION NAME="both_in_local_domain" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Determine if both points in a crossland pair are within the
 local domain for the processor. 
 </DESCRIPTION><IN NAME="nxl" TYPE="integer">
 Integer labeling the particular xlandmix pair
 </IN></FUNCTION><FUNCTION NAME="on_comp_domain" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Determine if the point is in comp-domain for the processor
 </DESCRIPTION><IN NAME="nxl" TYPE="integer">
 Integer labeling the particular xlandmix pair
 </IN><IN NAME="lx" TYPE="integer">
 lx=1,2 labels the point within an xlandmix pair
 </IN></FUNCTION><FUNCTION NAME="on_processor" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Determine if the point is on processor 
 </DESCRIPTION></FUNCTION><SUBROUTINE NAME="watermass_diag_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialization of watermass diagnostic output files. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="watermass_diag" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Diagnose effects from xlandmix on watermass transformation.  
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
