<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_shortwave_gfdl_mod" DATE="2012/06/01 20:47:08" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/sources"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> A. Rosati
</CONTACT><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> John P. Dunne
</CONTACT><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> S. M. Griffies 
</CONTACT><REVIEWER EMAIL="russell.fiedler@csiro.au"> Russell Fiedler 
</REVIEWER><OVERVIEW>
 This module returns thickness weighted and density weighted 
 temperature tendency [deg C *m/sec *kg/m^3] from penetrative 
 shortwave heating.
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute thickness and density weighted tendency [deg C *m/sec *kg/m^3]
 of temperature associated with penetrative shortwave heating in the upper
 ocean. Generally penetration is taken as a function of monthly optical 
 properties of the upper ocean, where optical properties are read 
 in from a file of climatological data or from an ecosystem model. 

 Presently there is account taken only of chlorophyll-a on the optical
 properties of ocean water.  Other particulates can be added so to 
 have a more complete picture of the ocean optical properties.

</DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
 Jerlov (1968): Optical Oceanography, Elsevier Press
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Morel and Antoine (1994), Heating rate in the upper ocean 
 in relation to its bio-optical state.
 Journal of Physical Oceanography vol 24 pages 1652-1664
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Manizza, M., C Le Quere, A. J. Watson, and E. T. Buitenhuis (2005)
 Bio-optical feedbacks among phytoplankton, upper ocean physics and 
 sea-ice in a global model. Geophys. Res. Let. 32, L05603, 
 doi:10.1029/2004GL020778
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Paulson and Simpson (1977)
 Irradiance measurements in the upper ocean
 Journal of Physical Oceanography vol 7 pages 952-956
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Rosati and Miyakoda (1988)
 A General Circulation Model for Upper Ocean Simulation
 Journal of Physical Oceanography vol 18 pages 1601-1626.
 </REFERENCE><NOTE>
 Optimized for vector peformance by R. Fiedler (russell.fiedler@csiro.au)
 June 2003 on the Australian NEC computer. 
 </NOTE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_shortwave_gfdl_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  Must be .true. to run with module. Default is false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="use_sw_morel_mom4p0" TYPE="logical">
  For backward compatibility with older simulations using 
  MOM4.0. The new subroutine removes some confusing and unnecessary
  logic to recompute a vertical k-index.  The differences 
  between the old and new approach are nonzero and so will
  result in bitwise changes to the simulation, but these changes
  are deemed to be trivial.  Default use_sw_morel_mom4p0=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="read_chl" TYPE="logical">
  If .true. then read in climatological data of chlorophyll-a.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="optics_morel_antoine" TYPE="logical">
  For using the Morel and Antoine optics.  This was the default in 
  MOM4.0 for use with chlorophyll data. This scheme is NOT available
  in MOM4p1 for use with the prognostic biology models, since it has 
  been improved by the Manizza scheme. 
  Default optics_morel_antoine=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="optics_manizza" TYPE="logical">
  For using the Manizza optics with chlorophyll data. Note that 
  when running with a prognostic biology model, GFDL scientists use the 
  Manizza optics.  
  Default optics_manizza=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sw_frac_top" TYPE="real">
  The fraction of shortwave radiation that should be incorporated into 
  the sw_source array at k=1.  The generic treatment in MOM is to assume
  that shortwave radiation is already contained inside the 
  T_prog(index_temp)%stf field. Hence, to avoid   
  double counting, sw_frac(k=0)=sw_frac_top should=0.0.
  If one removes shortwave from stf, then set sw_frac_top=1.0.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="zmax_pen" UNITS="meter" TYPE="real">
   Maximum depth of penetration of shortwave radiation. 
   Below this depth, shortwave penetration is exponentially 
   small and so is ignored.  This option formerly was useful,
   since computation of exponentials expensive.  But with more 
   modern computers, exponentials are cheap, so the default 
   has been changed from 200 to 1e6, making this option irrelevant.  
   But the option remains both for legacy purposes, and for those 
   computers where exponentials are not cheap.  
   Default zmax_pen=1e6.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="chl_default" UNITS="mg/m^3" TYPE="real">
   Default concentration chl_default=0.08 roughly yields Jerlov Type 1A optics.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="enforce_sw_frac" TYPE="logical">
  To ensure the shortwave fraction is monotonically decreasing with depth. 
  Applied only if optics_morel=.true.
  Default enforce_sw_frac=.true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="sw_morel_fixed_depths" TYPE="logical">
  To compute penetration assuming fixed depths via Grd%zw(k) depths.
  This is strictly incorrect when have undulating free surface and/or 
  generatlized vertical coordinates.  This option is here for purposes
  of legacy, as this was done in MOM4.0 versions. The default is 
  sw_morel_fixed_depths=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="override_f_vis" TYPE="logical">
  To fix the fraction of incoming shortwave assigned to the visible at 0.57.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="optics_for_uniform_chl" TYPE="logical">
  To set the coefficients for optical model assuming the chlorophyll 
  has a uniform distribution.  
  Default optics_for_uniform_chl=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging purposes.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="          axis_utils_mod"/><USE NAME="           constants_mod"/><USE NAME="        diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="       field_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="                 fms_mod"/><USE NAME="                 mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="time_interp_external_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="         ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="     ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_shortwave_gfdl_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialization for the shorwave module
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="sw_source_gfdl" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Add short wave penetrative heating to T_prog(index_temp)%th_tendency.

 Note that the divergence of shortwave for the first
 level "div_sw(0)" is compensating for the effect of having
 the shortwave component already included in the total
 surface tracer flux "stf(i,j,temp)"

 If the shortwave penetration routine is activated but Chlorophyll
 is not being read from data, then that implies that an ecological 
 model is being used to determine chlorophyll concentration.  
 In this case, the shortwave penetration is calcualted using the
 algorithm of

 Manizza, M., C Le Quere, A. J. Watson, and E. T. Buitenhuis (2005)
 Bio-optical feedbacks among phytoplankton, upper ocean physics and 
 sea-ice in a global model. Geophys. Res. Let. 32, L05603, 
 doi:10.1029/2004GL020778.

 This algorithm assumes that all infrared light is absorbed in the 
 top level.  It separates visible light into equal portions of 
 red and blue bands, treating separately absorption by water and
 chlorophyll.

 If the Chlorophyll is read from data, then we generally use the 
 Morel and Antoine optics scheme. Here, we take their approach 
 for computing a vertical profile based on the surface Chlorophyll. 
 However, one may also wish to use the Manizza scheme with 
 surface Chlorophyll data. In this case, we assume the surface
 Chlorophyll concentration is the same throughout the depth.
 This assumption is not generally good, but it does provide
 for a simple means of using Manizza etal scheme with Chlorophyll
 data. Note that GFDL scientists prefer Manizza etal for use with 
 prognostic 3d models.

 NOTE: Determine depths to T-points and W-points.
 This code is needed in particular for GEOPOTENTIAL, since
 depth_zwt and depth_zt for this coordinate do not include
 the surface height undulations. For the shortwave calculation,
 we wish to include the depth level undulations, unless enable
 sw_morel_fixed_depths=.true. 

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="sw_morel" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
  Solar shortwave energy penetrates below the ocean surface and is aborbed 
  by water and organic matter (both particulate and dissolved). This
  routine estimates fraction of shortwave penetration using chlorophyll-a.
  Absorbtion of shortwave radiation in the water assumes energy partitions
  between three exponentials:

  The first exponential is for wavelength &gt; 0.75 um (microns) and assumes a
  single attenuation of 0.267 m if the "zenith_angle" is 0.  Presently the 
  code assumes a zero zenith angle, but this could be modified easily. 

  The second and third exponentials represent a parameterization of the
  attenuation coeficient for light between 300 um and 750 um in the following
  form:

	E(z) = E(0) * [V1 *  exp(z/efold1) + V2 * exp(z/efold2)]
       with z &lt; 0 the ocean depth 

  Here, V1+V2=1 represent the partitioning between long (V1) and short (V2)
  wavelengths between 300 um and 750 um. Thoughout most of the ocean V1&lt;0.5
  and V2&gt;0.5. The "efold1" and "efold2" are the efolding depth of the long and short
  visable and ultra violet light. Throughout most of the ocean efold1 should not exceed 3 m
  while the efold2 will vary between 30 m in oligotrophic waters and 4 m in coastal
  regions. All of these constants are based on satellite estimates of chlorophyll a and
  taken from Morel and Antoine (JPO 1994, (24) 1652-1664).

  If the thickness of the first ocean level "dzt(1)" is 50 meters,
  then shortwave penetration does not do much. However, for higher
  vertical resolution, such as dzt(1) = 10 meters commonly used
  in ocean climate models, the effect of shortwave heating can
  be significant. This can be particularly noticable in the summer
  hemisphere.

 </DESCRIPTION><INFO><NOTE>
  The terms contributing to sw_fk(i,j) are depth independent
  when chl is depth independent.  However, we anticipate implementing 
  a biological model, whereby chl will be depth dependent.  
 </NOTE><NOTE>
  Simpson and Dickey (1981) and others have argued between one and 
  two exponentials for light between 300 um and 750 um.  
  With vertical grid resolution of 5 meters or finer
  for the upper 20 meters, the second exponential will make a difference.
  We anticipate using such resolutions, and so have implemented both 
  exponentials. 
 </NOTE></INFO></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="sw_morel_mom4p0" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 As in sw_morel, but uses the MOM4.0 algorithm to re-compute a k-level. 
 The recomputation is not needed, it can be costly, and produces
 no physically significant differences.  This routine is 
 retained for legacy only and it is not otherwise recommended.  
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
