<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_riverspread_mod" DATE="2012/06/01 20:47:08" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/sources"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> S.M. Griffies 
</CONTACT><OVERVIEW>
 Spread runoff or calving horizontally over a region determined 
 by a table. Also provide option to spread river runoff or calving
 through a diffusive operation. 
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 At some coastal ocean gridpoints, the runoff or calving flux contribution to 
 (p-e+r) may be very large because of local insertion to ocean. Therefore, 
 we may choose to spread the large river runoff over neighboring pairs
 of gridpoints. Annual mean river runoff greater than 0.05 m/day is 
 considered to be very large.
 This module allows one to spread the river using two options. 
 A/ by specifying river spreading table points
 B/ by performing a series of diffusion operations.
</DESCRIPTION><INFO><NOTE>
 Spreading in a 2D lat-long field is implemented in the following manner:

 A/ Table driven spreadging
 
 If the spreading region lives within the halo region
 (i.e., within same local_domain), 
 then no added mpp communication required. However, more generally 
 the spreading region can extend beyond the existing halo region.
 In this case, spread_domain
 is defined so that its halos incorporate the maximum separation 
 of spreading points.  New tracer and grid arrays
 are defined over this extended spread_domain.  This added domain
 size will come at some computational cost, so it is advantageous
 to choose the spreading region carefully.

 B/ Laplacian diffusion spreading

 Apply Laplacian operator to the river runoff/calving array to spread
 the river water abroad from the river mouth. 

 </NOTE><NOTE>
 The current implementation of table driven spreading has not 
 been tested for a spreading region that is separated by either 
 a zonal cyclic condition or across the tripolar fold.  
 </NOTE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_riverspread_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  Must be true to enable this module.  Default=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For debugging. Default=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="riverspread_diffusion" TYPE="logical">
  For spreading river water via a Laplacian diffusion operation.
  Default=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="riverspread_diffusion_passes" TYPE="integer">
  Number of diffusion passes applied to the runoff/calving array. 
  Default riverspread_diffusion_passes = 0.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="vel_micom_smooth" UNITS="m/sec" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM Laplacian mixing 
  coefficient used in the Laplacian smoothing of river water. 
  Default vel_micom_smooth=0.2.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="  field_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="            fms_mod"/><USE NAME="    mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="            mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_operators_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_types_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_riverspread_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
    Initial set up for spreading of tracers 

  A/ Table drive approach 
    (i,j) locations of points to be spread are set in data
    statements.

    Checks are performed to ensure that the spreading
    grid locations are valid according to model configuration.

    A summary of the locations of spreading points is written out.

    User specified inputs in "USER INPUT" section:

    ispread and jspread = user specified i,j grid locations of data for spreading.

    is, ie, js, je = user specified i,j grid locations of 
                     the corners of the spreading regions.
                     is and ie are the east and west coord of each region,
                     js and je are the south and north coord of each region. 

 B/ Laplacian approach requires minimal setup 

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="spread_river_horz" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Provide conservative spreading of river runoff field. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="riverspread_laplacian" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Provide conservative spreading of river runoff field using a 
 Laplacian operator.   
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><FUNCTION NAME="at_least_one_in_spread_domain" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Function to see if at least one of the points in the spreading region
 is within the computational domain for the processor. 
 </DESCRIPTION><IN NAME="nsp" TYPE="integer">
 Integer labeling the particular spreading region
 </IN></FUNCTION><FUNCTION NAME="on_comp_domain" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Determine if the point is in comp-domain for the processor
 </DESCRIPTION></FUNCTION><FUNCTION NAME="on_data_domain" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Determine if the point is in data-domain for the processor
 </DESCRIPTION></FUNCTION></MODULE>
