<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_nphysicsC_mod" DATE="2012/05/17 13:41:47" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/neutral"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> Stephen M. Griffies
</CONTACT><REVIEWER EMAIL="tim.leslie@gmail.com"> Tim Leslie
</REVIEWER><OVERVIEW>
 Thickness weighted and density weighted time tendency for tracer 
 from Laplacian neutral diffusion + Laplacian skew-diffusion.
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 This module computes the cell thickness weighted and density 
 weighted tracer tendency from small angle Laplacian neutral diffusion
 plus Laplacian skew-diffusion.  The algorithms for neutral diffusion
 are based on mom4p0d methods.  The algorithm for neutral skewsion 
 are based on a projection onto a few of the lowest baroclinic 
 modes. This module is experimental, and should be used with caution. 
</DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
 S.M. Griffies, A. Gnanadesikan, R.C. Pacanowski, V. Larichev, 
 J.K. Dukowicz,  and R.D. Smith
 Isoneutral diffusion in a z-coordinate ocean model
 Journal of Physical Oceanography (1998) vol 28 pages 805-830
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 S.M. Griffies 
 The Gent-McWilliams Skew-flux 
 Journal of Physical Oceanography (1998) vol 28 pages 831-841
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 R. Ferrari, S.M. Griffies, A.J.G. Nurser, and G.K. Vallis  
 A boundary value problem for the parameterized mesoscale eddy transport
 Ocean Modelling, Volume 32, 2010, Pages 143-156.
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 S.M. Griffies 
 Fundamentals of Ocean Climate Models (2004)
 Princeton University Press 
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 S.M. Griffies: Elements of MOM (2012)
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 D.B. Chelton,  R.A. deSzoeke, M.G. Schlax, K.E. Naggar, N. Siwertz
 Geographical Variability of the First Baroclinic Rossby Radius of Deformation
 Journal of Physical Oceanography (1998) vol 28 pages 433-460 
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 G. Danabasoglu and J. C. McWilliams
 Sensitivity of the global ocean circulation to 
 parameterizations of mesoscale tracer transports
 Journal of Climate (1995) vol 8 pages 2967--2987 
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Gerdes, Koberle, and Willebrand
 The influence of numerical advection schemes on the results of ocean
 general circulation models, Climate Dynamics (1991), vol. 5, 
 pages 211--226. 
 </REFERENCE><NOTE>
 Numerical implementation of the flux components follows the triad 
 approach documented in the references and implemented in MOM2 and MOM3.  
 The MOM algorithm accounts for partial bottom cells and generalized
 orthogonal horizontal coordinates and general vertical levels.  
 </NOTE><NOTE> 
 In steep neutral slope regions, neutral diffusive fluxes are tapered
 to zero with the tanh taper of Danabasoglu and McWilliams (1995) or the 
 quadratic scheme of Gerdes, Koberle, and Willebrand.  

 Traditional tapering is not required for the skew fluxes computed in 
 this module.  
 </NOTE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_nphysicsC_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  Must be true to use this module. Default is false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For printing starting and ending checksums for restarts
  </DATA><DATA NAME="epsln_bv_freq" UNITS="kg/m4" TYPE="real">
  Minimum buoyancy frequency accepted for the computation of 
  baroclinic modes. Default epsln_bv_freq=1e-10.  Note there 
  is also a minimum drhodz set in ocean_density.F90 via the
  nml epsln_drhodz in that module.  We provide yet another minimum
  here in case we need an extra regularization for the amplitude
  of the baroclinic modes.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="do_neutral_diffusion" TYPE="logical">
  To compute tendency from neutral diffusion.
  Default do_neutral_diffusion=.true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="do_gm_skewsion" TYPE="logical">
  To compute tendency from GM skewsion. Default do_gm_skewsion=.true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="gm_skewsion_modes" TYPE="logical">
  To compute tendency from GM skewsion using streamfunction established
  by baroclinic modes. Default gm_skewsion_modes=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="gm_skewsion_bvproblem" TYPE="logical">
  To compute tendency from GM skewsion using streamfunction established
  by a boundary value problem. Default gm_skewsion_bvproblem=.true.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="number_bc_modes" TYPE="integer">
  The number of baroclinic modes used to construct the eddy induced 
  streamfunction. Default number_bc_modes=1.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="bvp_bc_mode" TYPE="integer">
  The particular baroclinic mode used to construct the BVP streamfunction.
  If bvp_bc_mode=0, then will set bc_speed=0 when computing the BVP streamfunction.
  Default bvp_bc_mode=1.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="bvp_constant_speed" TYPE="logical">
  For taking a constant speed to be used for the calculation 
  of the BVP streamfunction. Default bvp_constant_speed=.false.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="bvp_speed" UNITS="m/s" TYPE="real">
  For setting the speed weighting the second order derivative operator 
  in the BVP streamfunction method: 
  c^2 = max[bvp_min_speed, (bvp_speed-c_mode)^2].
  If bvp_constant_speed, then  c^2 = bvp_speed^2. 
  Default bvp_speed=0.0, in which case c^2 = c_mode^2.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="bvp_min_speed" UNITS="m/s" TYPE="real">
  For setting a minimum speed for use with the calculation 
  of the BVP streamfunction. We need  bvp_min_speed&gt;0 to ensure
  that the second order derivative operator contributes to the 
  calculation of the streamfunction.  
  Default bvp_min_speed=0.1.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="bv_freq_smooth_vert" TYPE="logical">
  To smooth the buoyancy frequency for use in 
  computing the baroclinic modes. Generally this field has already 
  been smooted in ocean_density_mod, but we maintain the possibility of 
  further smoothing here.  Default bv_freq_smooth_vert=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="num_121_passes" TYPE="integer">
  The number of 121 passes used to smooth buoyancy frequency when 
  bv_freq_smooth_vert=.true.  Default num_121_passes=1.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="min_bc_speed" UNITS="m/s" TYPE="real">
  The minimum speed used for computing the baroclinic modes. 
  Default min_bc_speed=1e-6
  </DATA><DATA NAME="smooth_bc_modes" TYPE="logical">
  For doing a vertical 1-2-1 smoothing on the baroclinic modes
  prior to normalization.  This is useful to reduce noise.
  Default smooth_bc_modes=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="smooth_psi" TYPE="logical">
  For doing a horizontal 1-2-1 smoothing on the psix and psiy fields. 
  This is useful to reduce noise. Default smooth_psi=.true.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="regularize_psi" TYPE="logical">
  To reduce the magnitude of psi in regions of weak stratification, 
  using the slope = smax_psi to set the overall scale of the max allowed
  for psi. Default regularize_psi=.true.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="smax_modes" TYPE="real">
  Maximum slope used for setting the overall scale of a modal 
  contribution to the parameterized transport.   
  Default smax_psi=0.1.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="diffusion_all_explicit" TYPE="logical">
  To compute all contributions from neutral diffusion explicitly in time, including
  the K33 diagonal piece.  This approach is available only when have small time 
  steps and/or running with just a single tracer.  It is for testing purposes. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="neutral_physics_limit" TYPE="logical">
  When tracer falls outside a specified range, revert to horizontal 
  diffusive fluxes at this cell. This is an ad hoc and incomplete attempt
  to maintain monotonicity with the neutral physics scheme.  
  Default neutral_physics_limit=.true.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="tmask_neutral_on" TYPE="logical">
  If .true. then this logical reduces the neutral diffusive fluxes to 
  horizontal/vertical diffusion next to boundaries.  
  This approach has been found to reduce spurious 
  extrema resulting from truncation of triads used to compute 
  a neutral flux component.   
  Default tmask_neutral_on=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="dm_taper" TYPE="logical">
  Set to true to use the tanh tapering scheme of Danabasoglu and McWilliams.
  Default is true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="gkw_taper" TYPE="logical">
  Set to true to use the quadradic tapering scheme of Gerdes, Koberle, and Willebrand.
  Default is false. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="neutral_eddy_depth" TYPE="logical">
  Compute eddy_depth according to depth over which eddies feel the ocean surface.
  Default neutral_eddy_depth=.true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="turb_blayer_min" TYPE="real">
  Minimum depth of a surface turbulent boundary layer
  used in the transition of the neutral diffusion fluxes
  to the surface.  Note that in mom4p0, 
  turb_blayer_min was always set to zero. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="use_neutral_slopes_potrho" TYPE="logical">
  To compute the neutral slopes based on globally referenced potential 
  density rather than locally referenced potential density. This approach
  is meant solely for sensitivity studies; it is not meant for realistic 
  simulations.  
  Default use_neutral_slopes_potrho=.false. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="neutral_slopes_potrho_press" UNITS="dbar" TYPE="real">
  The reference pressure used to compute neutral slopes when setting
  use_neutral_slopes_potrho=.true. 
  Default neutral_slopes_potrho_press=2000.0
  </DATA><DATA NAME="smooth_advect_transport" TYPE="logical">
  For doing a horizontal 1-2-1 smoothing on the diagnosed  
  uhrho_et_gm and vhrho_nt_gm fields.  
  Default smooth_advect_transport=.true.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="smooth_advect_transport_num" TYPE="integer">
  Number of iterations for the smooothing of horizontal transport. 
  Default smooth_advect_transport_num=2.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="          constants_mod"/><USE NAME="       diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="                fms_mod"/><USE NAME="             fms_io_mod"/><USE NAME="        mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="                mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="       time_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="      ocean_density_mod"/><USE NAME="      ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_nphysics_util_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_operators_mod"/><USE NAME="   ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_tracer_diag_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_tracer_util_mod"/><USE NAME="        ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="         ocean_util_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_nphysicsC_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialize the neutral physics module by registering fields for 
 diagnostic output and performing some numerical checks to see 
 that namelist settings are appropriate. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="nphysicsC" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 This function computes the thickness weighted and density weighted
 time tendency for tracer from neutral physics.  Full discussion
 and details are provided by Griffies (2008). 

 Here is a brief summary.  

---How the neutral diffusive flux components are computed:

 The vertical flux component is split into diagonal (3,3) and 
 off-diagonal (3,1) and (3,2) terms. The off-diagonal (3,1) and (3,2) 
 terms are included explicitly in time. The main contribution from the 
 (3,3) term to the time tendency is included implicitly in time 
 along with the usual contribution from diapycnal processes 
 (vertical mixing schemes).  This is the K33_implicit term.
 This approach is necessary with high vertical resolution, as 
 noted by Cox (1987).  However, splitting the vertical flux into 
 an implicit and explicit piece compromises the 
 integrity of the vertical flux component (see Griffies et al. 1998).
 So to minimize the disparity engendered by this split, the portion of 
 K33 that can be stably included explicitly in time is computed along 
 with the (3,1) and (3,2) terms. 
 
 All other terms in the mixing tensor are included explicitly in time
 using a forward time step as required for temporal stability of 
 numerical diffusive processes.  

 The off-diagonal terms in the horizontal flux components, and all terms
 in the vertical flux component, are tapered in regions of steep neutral
 slope according to the requirements of linear stability.  MOM allows for 
 choice of two tapering schemes:

 (a) the tanh taper of Danabasoglu and McWilliams (1995)
 (b) the quadratic scheme of Gerdes, Koberle, and Willebrand (1991)

 Linear stability is far less stringent on the diagonal (1,1) and (2,2)
 part of the horizontal flux.  Indeed, these terms in practice need
 not be tapered in steep sloped regions. 

---How the skew diffusive flux components are computed:

 The skew flux components are purely off-diagonal.  
 They are computed based on a vector streamfunction which 
 is built from a sum of baroclinic modes. 
 It is this part of the calculation that differs from 
 ocean_nphysicsA and ocean_nphysicsB.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="neutral_blayer" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the boundary layer as determined by 
 1. depth within which typical mesoscale eddies are partially outcropped
 2. depth within which vertical mixing scheme (e.g., kpp) computes a boundary layer

 Determine depth over which mesoscale eddies feel the ocean 
 surface.  This depth is a function of the neutral slope 
 and the Rossby radius.  This depth is called "eddy_depth".
 The algorithm for computing this depth is taken from 
 the appendix to Large etal, 1997 JPO vol 27, 2418-2447. 
 
 In addition to considering mesoscale eddy lengths,
 include the possibility that the diabatic vertical
 mixing (e.g., KPP) produces a mixed layer depth that is 
 deeper than the depth that mesoscale eddies feel the ocean 
 surface.  Include this surf_blthick in the considerations so 
 to determine the depth of this generalized "boundary layer" 
 and the neutral slope at the base of the boundary layer. 

 Note: Only consider surface boundary layers here.  

 This subroutine is a modification of that in ocean_nphysicsA. 
 Here, we only compute the eddy_depth based on the
 algorithm in Large etal.  We do not compute an eddy
 depth which is also a function of smax. that is, we 
 remove the ocean_nphysicsA portion of the calculation 
 that sits inside the neutral_linear_gm_taper if-test.   
 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="compute_ndiffusion" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine to compute the tendency from neutral diffusion.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="compute_gmskewsion" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine to compute the tracer tendency from GM skewsion.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="baroclinic_modes" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the baroclinic wave speeds and the dimensionless
 baroclinic mode eigenfunction for the vertical velocity baroclinic 
 modes.  These modes vanish at the surface and the bottom.  We use
 the Chelton etal WKB analytic formulae for the speeds and modes.

 The baroclinic modes are dimensionless, and normalized over the 
 depth of the ocean, from free surface to bottom.  

 Units of the speeds are m/sec.

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="compute_psi_modes" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute vector streamfunction as projection onto baroclinic modes.

 Units of psi are m^2/sec

 This method for computing the quasi-Stokes streamfunction 
 is not generally recommended. It remains in MOM only for 
 testing purposes.  

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="compute_psi_bvp" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute vector streamfunction by solving a boundary value problem. 

 psi is centered on bottom of tracer cell; for example, 
 psi(k=1)=psi at bottom of tracer cell k=1.
 psi vanishes at the ocean surface: psi(k=0)=0
 and ocean bottom: psi(k=kmt)=0.

 psix is centred on north face of tracer cell
 psiy is centred on east  face of tracer cell

 Solve for psi(k=1,kmt-1) using a tridiagonal solver from 
 Section 2.4 of Press etal 1986.

 Units of psi are m^2/sec

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="fz_terms" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the tracer independent pieces of the vertical 
 flux component. As a result of this routine, 
 Array tensor_31 = x-diffusivity*slope (m^2/sec) for fz
 Array tensor_32 = y-diffusivity*slope (m^2/sec) for fz 

 K33 is the (3,3) term in small angle Redi diffusion tensor.
 It is broken into an explicit in time piece and implicit 
 in time piece.  It is weighted by density for non-Boussinesq
 and rho0 for Boussinesq.  

 K33 has units (kg/m^3)*m^2/sec.

 Also will compute the squared Eady growth rate, with the maximum
 slope contributing to this growth rate set by smax.

 This routine is nearly the same as in ocean_nphysicsA, except 
 for the following changes: 
 1/ the routine here removes all pieces related to GM-skewsion.  
 2/ the routine here uses Thickness%depth_zwt rather than Grd%zt. 

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="fx_flux_ndiffuse" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the zonal neutral diffusion tracer flux component.
 Compute this component for all tracers at level k.

 fx has physical dimensions (area*diffusivity*density*tracer gradient)

 This routine is the same as that in ocean_nphysicsA, except 
 for the following changes: 
 1/ the routine here removes all pieces related to GM-skewsion.  
 2/ the routine here uses Thickness%depth_zwt rather than Grd%zt. 
 3/ ah_array is removed.

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="fy_flux_ndiffuse" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the meridional neutral diffusion tracer flux component.
 Compute this component for all tracers at level k.

 fy has physical dimensions (area*diffusivity*density*tracer gradient)

 This routine is the same as that in ocean_nphysicsA, except 
 for the following changes: 
 1/ the routine here removes all pieces related to GM-skewsion.  
 2/ the routine here uses Thickness%depth_zwt rather than Grd%zt. 
 3/ ah_array is removed.

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="fz_flux_ndiffuse" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the vertical neutral diffusion tracer flux component.
 Compute this component for all tracers at level k.
 Surface and bottom boundary condition fz(k=0)=fz(k=kmt(i,j))=0

 fz has physical dimensions (density*diffusivity*tracer gradient)

 This is nearly the same as the subroutine in ocean_nphysicsA. 

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="fx_flux_gm" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the zonal GM tracer flux component.
 Compute this component for all tracers at level k.

 fx has physical dimensions (area*diffusivity*density*tracer gradient)

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="fy_flux_gm" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the meridional GM tracer flux component.
 Compute this component for all tracers at level k.

 fy has physical dimensions (area*diffusivity*density*tracer gradient)

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="fz_flux_gm" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the vertical GM tracer flux component.
 Compute this component for all tracers at level k.
 Surface and bottom boundary condition fz(k=0)=fz(k=kmt(i,j))=0

 fz has physical dimensions (density*diffusivity*tracer gradient)

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="invtri_bvp" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Solve the vertical diffusion equation implicitly using the
 method of inverting a tridiagonal matrix as described in
 Numerical Recipes in Fortran, The art of Scientific Computing,
 Second Edition, Press, Teukolsky, Vetterling, Flannery, 1992
 pages 42,43.

 enforce upsilon(k=kmt) = 0 via use of mask(k+1).  

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="compute_advect_transport" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Diagnose advective mass transport from GM. 

 This routine is a diagnostic routine since generically we use the 
 skewsion approach for the GM scheme. However, it could form the 
 basis for an advective implementation of GM, which remains to be done.

 Comments on the diagnostic scheme:
 
 0/ algorithm based on a similar approach used for submeso parameterization.  

 1/ psiy(k) is centred at bottom of tracer cell at zonal face.
    so -(psiy(i,j,k-1)-psiy(i,j,k)) gives zonal transport through 
    tracer cell k.  

 2/ psix(k) is centred at bottom of tracer cell at meridional face.
    so (psix(i,j,k-1)-psix(i,j,k)) gives meridional transport through 
    tracer cell k.  

 3/ compute vertical component from convergence of horizontal, just
 as for the vertical velocity component for the Eulerian transport.
 
 4/ wrho_bt_gm(:,:,k=0) = 0.0 by definition
 it should be diagnosed to have zero at the ocean bottom; we should
 check that this is indeed the case to verify the diagnostic algorithm.

 5/ expand the BDX_ET and BDY_NT operators for efficiency.  

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_nphysicsC_restart" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
  Write out restart files registered through register_restart_file
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_nphysicsC_end" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Write to restart.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
