<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_nphysics_util_mod" DATE="2012/05/17 13:41:47" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_param/neutral"><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> Stephen M. Griffies
</CONTACT><REVIEWER EMAIL="tim.leslie@gmail.com"> Tim Leslie
</REVIEWER><OVERVIEW>
 Utilities for neutral physics, including the code to compute 
 space-time dependent diffusivities.  
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 Utilities for neutral physics, including the code to compute 
 space-time dependent diffusivities and many diagnostics.  
</DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
 D.B. Chelton,  R.A. deSzoeke, M.G. Schlax, K.E. Naggar, N. Siwertz
 Geographical Variability of the First Baroclinic Rossby Radius of Deformation
 Journal of Physical Oceanography (1998) vol 28 pages 433-460 
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 G. Danabasoglu and J. C. McWilliams
 Sensitivity of the global ocean circulation to 
 parameterizations of mesoscale tracer transports
 Journal of Climate (1995) vol 8 pages 2967--2987 
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Held and Larichev
 A scaling theory for horizontally homogeneous baroclinically 
 unstable flow on a beta plane
 Journal of Atmospheric Sciences (1996) vol 53 pages 946-952
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 M. Visbeck, J.C. Marshall, T. Haine and M. Spall
 Specification of eddy transfer coefficients in coarse resolution ocean
 circulation models
 Journal of Physical Oceanography (1997) vol 27 pages 381--402
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 D. Ferreira, J. Marshall, and P. Heimbach, 
 Estimating eddy stresses by fitting dynamics to observations 
 using a residual-mean ocean circulation omdel and its adjoint. 
 Journal of Physical Oceanography (2005) vol 35 pages 1891-1910.
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 K. Eden, Eddy length scales in the North Atlantic, 2007,
 Preprint. 
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 K. Eden and R. Greatbatch, 2008: Towards a mesoscale eddy closure,
 Ocean Modelling, vol. 20, pages 223-239
 </REFERENCE><NOTE>
 Diffusivities can be determined in a number of manners

 TIME INDEPENDENT

 Various methods are available for specifying a time 
 independent diffusivity, either globally uniform or 
 with selections of spatial dependence.  

 TIME DEPENDENT (as a function of the flow)

 Various methods are available for determining the 
 diffusivity that changes in time according to the 
 properties of the fluid.  There are various means 
 for specifying the length and time scales needed
 to set the diffusivity. 

 LENGTH SCALES 

 1. First baroclinic Rossby radius (estimated as per Chelton etal).  
 Equatorial Rossby radius is used within 5deg of the equator.
 
 2. Width of the baroclinic zone, as done in the Hadley Centre 
 model and documented in the MOM3 Manual.

 3. Specified length scale set independent of the flow. 

 TIME SCALE 

 When using either of the above for the length scale, 
 the time scale is determined by the Eady growth rate.    

 COMBINED LENGTH/TIME SCALE 
 
 Another option, used in the GFDL CM2.X coupled climate models,
 is to set the diffusivity proportional to the depth averaged
 absolute value of the horizontal density gradient.  
 </NOTE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_nphysics_util_nml"><DATA NAME="debug_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  For printing starting and ending checksums for restarts
  </DATA><DATA NAME="nphysics_util_zero_init" TYPE="logical">
  For Time%init=.true. and wishing to ensure starting with a clean 
  suite of nphysics_util fields, even if ocean_neutral.res.nc exists.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="epsln_drhodz" UNITS="kg/m^3" TYPE="real">
  For computing drhodz used in slope calculation.
  We must keep drhodz &lt; 0 in order to maintain integrity of the 
  quasi-Stokes streamfunction as well as computation of buoyancy frequency.  
  Default epsln_drhodz=1e-30.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="drhodz_mom4p1" TYPE="logical">
  For computing the vertical deriviative of locally referenced
  potrho as in the preferred MOM algorithm rather than the 
  earlier mom4p0 approach. Default drhodz_mom4p1=.true.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="drhodz_smooth_horz" TYPE="logical">
  For horizontal laplacian smoothing the vertical derivative 
  of density prior to its use in computing the neutral slopes. 
  This smoothing helps to produce regularized slopes.  
  Note that this option breaks the integrity of the triads
  and is thus NOT generally recommended.  
  Default drhodz_smooth_horz=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="drhodz_smooth_vert" TYPE="logical">
  For vertical 1-2-1 smoothing the vertical derivative of 
  density prior to its use in computing the neutral slopes.
  This smoothing helps to produce regularized slopes.  
  Note that this option breaks the integrity of the triads
  and is thus NOT generally recommended.  
  Default drhodz_smooth_vert=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="vel_micom_smooth" UNITS="m/sec" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM Laplacian mixing 
  coefficient used in smoothing of drhodzb. 
  Default vel_micom_smooth=0.2. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="num_121_passes" TYPE="integer">
  For number of 1-2-1 passes through to smooth drhodz or 
  eady_rate in vertical. Default num_121_passes=1. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="aredi" TYPE="real">
  Neutral diffusivity used for experiments using a constant diffusivity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm" TYPE="real">
  GM-skew diffusivity used for experiments using a constant diffusivity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="aredi_equal_agm" TYPE="logical">
  Will set aredi_array=agm_array, over-riding any other specification 
  of aredi_array. Default aredi_equal_agm=.true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="smax" TYPE="real">
  Value of the maximum neutral direction slope above which the neutral fluxes are 
  either tapered to zero or saturated.  Typical value is smax=0.01 or smaller. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="swidth" TYPE="real">
  Width in slope over which use tanh with dm_taper scheme to taper fluxes in 
  steep sloped regions. Typical value swidth=0.1*smax
  </DATA><DATA NAME="smax_grad_gamma_scalar" TYPE="real">
  For calculation of gradients of scalars along a neutral direction, then 
  when abs(slope) &gt; smax_grad_gamma_scalar, will compute the gradient using 
  only the vertical scalar gradient, since the slopes are so large they are 
  effectively infinite. 
  Default smax_grad_gamma_scalar=.01 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="neutral_horz_mix_bdy" TYPE="logical">
  If .true., then use a horizontal diffusivity in the neutral boundary layer. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="vel_micom_bdy" UNITS="m/sec" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM horizontal diffusivity 
  within the neutral boundary layer. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="ah_bdy" UNITS="m^2/sec" TYPE="real">
  Constant horizontal diffusivity for the boundary layer.  
  Default ah_bdy=0.0.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="tracer_mix_micom" TYPE="logical">
  If .true., then the GM-skew diffusivity is set according to a velocity scale 
  times the grid spacing. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="vel_micom" UNITS="m/sec" TYPE="real">
  Velocity scale that is used for computing the MICOM diffusivity. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_lat_zones" TYPE="logical">
  If true, will set agm_array as constant within two latitudinal zones.  
  The idea is that one may wish to use a larger agm in the ACC than 
  elsewhere. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_lat_zones_boundary" TYPE="real">
  Boundary between agm in the south and north zones. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_lat_zones_ratio" TYPE="real">
  Ratio between the large agm used in the southern latitudinal zone
  to that used in the north.  
  agm_array(north) = agm
  agm_array(south) = agm*agm_lat_zones_ratio
  </DATA><DATA NAME="bryan_lewis_aredi" TYPE="logical">
  Set bryan_lewis_aredi=.true. when want to have aredi a function of depth
  according to the Bryan and Lewis (1979) profile. Maintained for legacy 
  purposes, and not recommended for new models.                                 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="ahs" TYPE="real">
  ahs = adjustable parameter at the surface for bryan_lewis_aredi   
  </DATA><DATA NAME="ahb" TYPE="real">
  ahb = adjustable parameter at the bottom for bryan_lewis_aredi   
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_read_restart" TYPE="logical">
  For those cases with agm_closure=.false. where we wish to read in 
  the agm_array from restart files and keep the value from the restart.
  This approach allows us to read in a spatially dependent agm_array 
  that may have been computed from another integration, but to leave
  the coefficient static in time.  
  Default agm_read_restart=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure" TYPE="logical">
  If .true. then will compute the GM-skew diffusivity as a function of the flow.
  The length scale is determined by the Rossby radius and the time scale is 
  determined by the Eady growth rate.  Diffusivities are depth independent.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_max" UNITS="m^2/sec" TYPE="real">
  Maximum GM diffusivity allowed when using agm_closure=.true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_min" UNITS="m^2/sec" TYPE="real">
  Minimum GM diffusivity allowed when using agm_closure=.true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_scaling" UNITS="dimensionless" TYPE="logical">
  Dimensionless tuning parameter for computing flow dependent diffusivities. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_upper_depth" UNITS="m" TYPE="real">
  Upper depth where start the depth integration to compute the Eady 
  growth rate and/or baroclinicity.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_lower_depth" UNITS="m" TYPE="real">
  Deeper depth where finish the depth integration to compute the Eady 
  growth rate and/or baroclinicity.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_n2_scale" TYPE="logical">
  For computing the agm coefficient using a 3-dimensional 
  scaling by (N/Nref)^2, with N=buoyancy frequency and 
  Nref the buoyancy frequency at the base of the neutral 
  blayer. Default agm_closure_n2_scale=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_n2_scale_coeff" UNITS="m^2/s" TYPE="real">
  Coefficient setting the scale for the diffusivity computed from 
  agm_closure_n2_scale. 
  Default agm_closure_n2_scale_coeff=1e3. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_n2_scale_nref_cst" TYPE="logical">
  For taking the reference buoyancy frequency as agm_closure_buoy_freq
  for the (N/Nref)^2 scaling.  
  Default agm_closure_n2_scale_nref_cst=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_baroclinic" TYPE="logical">
  For computing the agm coefficient using only the vertically
  averaged magnitude of the horizontal density gradient 
  (i.e., the "baroclinicity").
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_buoy_freq" UNITS="sec^-1" TYPE="real">
  For computing the agm coefficient using only the vertically
  averaged horizontal density gradient, we need to specify a 
  buoyancy frequency,  which is taken to be fixed over all space-time.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_length_cap" TYPE="logical">
  For setting a maximum length scale for the agm_closure calculation.
  Default agm_closure_length_cap=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_length_max" UNITS="metre" TYPE="real">
  Maximum length scale used for computing agm_closure.  
  Default agm_closure_length_max=50e3.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_length_fixed" TYPE="logical">
  Use fixed length scale for computing agm_closure diffusivity 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_length" UNITS="meter" TYPE="real">
  Fixed length scale for use with agm_closure_fixed_length
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_length_rossby" TYPE="logical">
  For computing the agm_closure length scale according to Rossby radius. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="rossby_radius_max" UNITS="meter" TYPE="real">
  Maximum Rossby radius used for agm_closure_length_rossby and 
  the neutral_sine_taper. Default = 100e3 m.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="rossby_radius_min" UNITS="meter" TYPE="real">
  Minimum Rossby Radius used for agm_closure_length_rossby and 
  the neutral_sine_taper. Default = 15e3 m.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_length_bczone" TYPE="logical">
  For computing the agm_closure length scale according to radius of baroclinic zone. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="bczone_max_pts" TYPE="integer">
  Max number of horizontal grid points for use in computing the baroclinic zone radius.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_bczone_crit_rate" UNITS="sec^-1" TYPE="real">
  Critical growth rate for determining width of the baroclinic zone. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_growth_scale" UNITS="dimensionless" TYPE="real">
  Dimensionless scaling used to set a maximum for agm_growth. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_eden_greatbatch" TYPE="logical">
  For computing the agm_closure length scale according to minimum 
  of the Rhines scale and the Rossby radius, and using 3d Eady 
  growth rate. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_eden_gamma" TYPE="real" UNITS="dimensionless">
  For use in regularizing the growth rate used in the eden/greatbatch approach.
  Default agm_closure_eden_gamma=200. Setting to zero removes the regularization.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_eden_length_const" TYPE="logical">
  To set the length scale for agm_closure_eden_greatbatch to constant. 
  Default agm_closure_eden_length_const=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_eden_length" TYPE="real" UNITS="metre">
  Length scale for use with agm_closure_eden_length_const=.true.
  Default agm_closure_eden_length=10e3. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_eady_smooth_vert" TYPE="logical">
  For vertical 1-2-1 smoothing the eady_rate 
  Default agm_closure_eady_smooth=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_eady_smooth_horz" TYPE="logical">
  For horizontal Laplacian smoothing of eady growth rate. 
  Default agm_closure_eady_smooth_horz=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_eady_cap" TYPE="logical">
  For capping the eady growth rate to avoid huge values.  
  Default agm_closure_eady_cap=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_eady_ave_mixed" TYPE="logical">
  To set the Eady growth rate to its average within mixed layer region.  
  This is used to avoid spuriously large values which often appear just 
  in the upper regions of the ocean mixed layer.  
  Default agm_closure_eady_ave_mixed=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_smooth_space" TYPE="logical">
  For smoothing the agm diffusivity in space when nonconstant diffusivity used. 
  Default is agm_smooth_space=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_smooth_time" TYPE="logical">
  For smoothing the agm diffusivity in time when nonconstant diffusivity used. 
  Default is agm_smooth_time=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_damping_time" UNITS="days" TYPE="real">
  The damping time used for time smoothing agm_array.
  Default agm_damping_time=10days.  
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_grid_scaling" TYPE="logical">
  For an overall scaling of the agm coefficient, according to
  the relative resolution of the grid and deformation radius. 
  Default is agm_closure_grid_scaling=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="agm_closure_grid_scaling_power" TYPE="real">
  Power used to scale the agm_closure diffusivity. 
  Default is agm_closure_grid_scaling_power=2.0
  </DATA><DATA NAME="aredi_diffusivity_grid_scaling" TYPE="logical">
  For an overall scaling of the aredi coefficient, according to
  the relative resolution of the grid and deformation radius.
  This option is used only when aredi_equal_agm=.false. 
  Default is aredi_diffusivity_grid_scaling=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="epsln_drhodz_diagnostics" UNITS="kg/m4" TYPE="real">
  For drhodz used in calculation of dianeutral velocity component
  from cabbeling and thermobaricity.
  Default epsln_drhodz_diagnostics=1e-7.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="wdianeutral_smooth" TYPE="logical">
  For smoothing the diagnosed dianeutral velocity component using a 
  horizontal 1-2-1 smoother. Default is wdianeutral_smooth=.true.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="smooth_eta_tend_gm90" TYPE="logical">
  For smoothing the diagnosed contribution to steric sea level 
  time tendency associated with the GM90 scheme. 
  Default is smooth_eta_tend_gm90=.false.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="        constants_mod"/><USE NAME="     diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="              fms_mod"/><USE NAME="           fms_io_mod"/><USE NAME="              mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="      mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="     time_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_domains_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_density_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_operators_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_tracer_diag_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_tracer_util_mod"/><USE NAME="      ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="       ocean_util_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_nphysics_util_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialize the utility module for neutral physics.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="cabbeling_thermob_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialize the cabbeling and thermobaricity related diagnostic 
 fields and register the diagnostics to the diag manager. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_nphysics_coeff_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialize the diffusivities used in neutral physics.
 Need to initialize them after the ocean_nphysics_util_init routine,
 since need to have the domain parameters known for passing the 
 array size information into the ocean_nphysics_coeff_init routine. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="tracer_derivs" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute the tracer derivatives.

 Horizontal derivatives are taken along surfaces of 
 constant vertical coordinate (constant k-level)

 This approach ensures that when neutral physics defaults to "horizontal" physics
 next to boundaries, it will do so as horizontal, defined along surfaces of constant 
 s-surfaces, and so will not generate spurious extrema.  

 Additionally, when using generalized vertical coordinates, the neutral diffusion
 slope should be computed relative to the s-surfaces.  The skew diffusion slope 
 should ideally be computed with respect to z-surfaces, as z-surfaces define
 available potential energy. However, when s and z surfaces are reasonably close, 
 as they are in the interior for zstar and pstar vertical coordinates, then we 
 choose to to dissipate thickness as defined relative to the zstar or pstar surfaces. 
 This should not be such a big deal, and it is certainly easier computationally than
 worrying about computing two separate sets of slopes.  More on this detail is 
 discussed in "Elements of MOM".
 
 NOTE: This approach is not appropriate for sigma-models. Indeed, many assumptions
 in the neutral physics modules need to be rethought for terrain following vertical
 coordinates. 

 Vertical neutral density derivative for use in fz_terms
 and fz_flux, and for use in fx_flux and fy_flux. 
 Note that the derivative at k=nk vanishes by definition
 since these derivatives are at the bottom of tracer cell. 
 also note the use of -epsln_drhodz ensures the vertical 
 derivative is always &lt; 0.  We also support the same 
 approach used in the mom4p0d code for legacy purposes. 

 Comments about smoothing drhodz:

 1/ Tests in coupled 1-degree model showed extreme sensitivity 
 of MOC to smoothing.  GFDL users generally do NOT smooth, hence
 the default drhodz_smooth_vert=drhodz_smooth_horz=.false. 

 2/ Smoothing the vertical derivative of drhodzb and drhodzh helps  
 is greatly needed for producing a regularized (i.e., well behaved)
 neutral slope vector.  

 3/ An attempt was made to smooth dTdz and dSdz rather 
 than drhodz.  The resulting slope was smooth, but not as 
 smooth as when acting on drhodz itself.

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="neutral_slopes" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the neutral slopes for the triads associated 
 with the vertical flux component.  

 Array tensor_31 initially holds the x-slope used for flux component fz.
 Array tensor_32 initially holds the y-slope used for flux component fz.

 In subsequent calculations, these arrays will be multipied by the
 diffusivities.  

 No slope tapering is applied in this routine. 

 slopes are computed over k=1,nk-1, since the slope at k=nk 
 should be zero. 

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="compute_eady_rate" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Finish computing eady growth rate.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="compute_baroclinicity" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Finish computing baroclinicity, which is defined to be the vertically
 averaged magnitude of the horizontal density gradient.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="compute_rossby_radius" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the first baroclinic Rossby radius of deformation. 
 Employ WKB approach described by Chelton et al.  In particular, 
 use formulae (2.2), (2.3a) and (2.3b) from their paper. 

 Place a max and min value on the Rossby radius.

 Compute buoyancy frequency in terms of vertical gradient of 
 locally referenced potential density.  Place the reference point
 at the interface between the tracer cells, which is also where 
 the vertical derivative of neutral density is located.  This amounts 
 to a centered difference computation similar to that used by 
 Chelton et al. equation (B.4). 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="compute_bczone_radius" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the radius of the baroclinic zone in a manner 
 suggested by the Hadley Centre approach (Malcolm Roberts, personal 
 communication).  

 Algorithm is used in MOM3 and documented in the MOM3 Manual.

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="compute_diffusivity" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes flow dependent diffusivity.
 Allow for an added dimensionless tuning factor as well as a 
 minimum and maximum diffusivity. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="transport_on_nrho_gm" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Classify horizontal GM mass transport according to neutral density classes. 

 NOTE: This diagnostic works with transport integrated from bottom to 
 a particular cell depth. To get transport_on_nrho_gm, a remapping is 
 performed, rather than the binning done for trans_rho.  

 Code history 
 2008: algorithm based (incorrectly) on transport_on_rho 
 2009: algorithm corrected to be consistent with remapping 
       used in tracer_on_rho algorithm
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="transport_on_rho_gm" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Classify horizontal GM mass transport according to potential density classes. 

 Algorithm based on linear interpolation of function on s-surfaces to 
 function on rho-surfaces.  

 Diagnostic makes sense when potrho is monotonically increasing with 
 depth, although the algorithm does not explicitly make this assumption.  

 NOTE: This diagnostic works with transport integrated from bottom to 
 a particular cell depth. To get transport_on_rho_gm, a remapping is 
 performed, rather than the binning done for trans_rho.  

 Code history 

 2008: algorithm based (incorrectly) on transport_on_rho 
 2009: algorithm corrected to be consistent with remapping 
       used in tracer_on_rho algorithm

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="transport_on_theta_gm" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Classify horizontal GM mass transport according to potential temp classes. 

 Algorithm based on linear interpolation of function on s-surfaces to 
 function on rho-surfaces.  

 Diagnostic makes sense when potential temp is monotonically increasing 
 with depth, although the algorithm does not explicitly make this assumption.  

 NOTE: This diagnostic works with transport integrated from bottom to 
 a particular cell depth. To get transport_on_theta_gm, a remapping is 
 performed, rather than the binning done for trans_rho.  

 Code history 

 2009: algorithm based on transport_on_rho_gm

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="compute_eta_tend_gm90" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Diagnose contribution to global mean sea level evolution arising  
 from analytic form of Gent-McWilliams scheme.

 This routine computes the diagnostic based on an analytic form of the 
 GM90 contribution.  The raw numerical form is computed inside the respective
 nphysics modules.  The raw numerical form is more accurate and thus
 recomended for purposes of sea level budgets.  

 Compute an averaged slope using tensor_31 and tensor_32.
 Then compute the neutral divergence of this slope vector, just
 as if each component of the slope was a scalar.  

 To avoid stencil issues with bottom cells, mask to zero 
 contributions from cells next to the bottom in either of the
 three directions.  

 Send output to diagnostic manager. 
 
 Subroutine history: 
 Feb2010 version 1.0: Stephen.Griffies 
 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="cabbeling_thermob_tendency" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute tendencies from cabbeling and thermobaricity.

 To avoid stencil issues with bottom cells, mask to zero 
 contributions from cells next to the bottom in either of the
 three directions.  

 Set cabbeling and thermobaricity to zero in regions where 
 vertical stratification is gravitationally unstable.  The idea is 
 that in such regions, convective mixing will wash away the impact of 
 along-neutral diffusion, in which case cabbeling and thermobaricity 
 are not relevant anyhow.  

 Set the vertical stratification drho_dz to a negative number 
 with lower bound on its magnitude as set by epsln_drhodz_diagnostics.

 Send output to diagnostic manager. 
 
 Subroutine history: 
 Jan2010 version 1.0: initial coding by Stephen.Griffies  
 Mar2010 version 2.0: tweaks on the division by drho_dz and strat_mask
 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="pressure_derivs" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Compute the pressure derivatives for use in thermobaricity diagnostic.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="calc_gradx_gamma_scalar" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the i-gradient along neutral surfaces
 for a scalar field. For use in the cabbeling and thermobaricity 
 diagnostic.  Thus, when slope is steep, the full derivative is 
 tapered, rather than just the off-diagonal term. 

 We only compute neutral i-gradient for interior regions,
 since will be setting thermobaricity and cabbeling to zero at 
 top and bottom levels; do not trust the calculation at top 
 and bottom boundaries due to stencil truncations. 

 Algorithm slightly modified from ocean_nphysC calculation of 
 neutral diffusion x-flux.  
 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="calc_grady_gamma_scalar" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Subroutine computes the y-gradient along neutral surfaces
 for a scalar field. For use in the cabbeling and thermobaricity 
 diagnostic.  Thus, when slope is steep, the full derivative is 
 tapered, rather than just the off-diagonal term. 

 We only compute neutral y-gradient for interior regions,
 since will be setting thermobaricity and cabbeling to zero at 
 top and bottom levels; do not trust the calculation at top 
 and bottom boundaries due to stencil truncations.  

 Algorithm slightly modified from ocean_nphysC calculation of 
 neutral diffusion y-flux.  
 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="watermass_diag_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialization of watermass diagnostic output files. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="watermass_diag" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Diagnose effects from nphysics on the watermass transformation.
 For use with nphysicsA and nphysicsB. 
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="watermass_diag_ndiffuse" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>

  Diagnose watermass transformation from neutral diffusion. 
  For use with the nphysicsC scheme.  

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="watermass_diag_sdiffuse" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>

  Diagnose watermass transformation from skew diffusion. 
  For use with the neutral physics C scheme.  

 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_nphysics_util_restart" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
  Write out restart files registered through register_restart_file
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="ocean_nphysics_coeff_end" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Write to restart.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
