<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_blob_dynamic_bottom_mod" DATE="0000/00/00 00:00:00" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_blobs"><CONTACT EMAIL="m.bates@student.unsw.edu.au"> Michael L. Bates
</CONTACT><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> Stephen M. Griffies
</CONTACT><OVERVIEW>
 This module runs the dynamic bottom blob implementation of the embedded 
 Lagrangian buoyancy blob framework. The module forms new dynamic 
 bottom blobs, integrates the properties of existing blobs, and handles
 the transfer of free blobs to bottom blobs.
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 Bottom blobs are formed using the subroutine dynamic_bottom_form_new,
 which is called from the main blob driver module.  Bottom blobs are
 formed explicitly in time, directly after the integration of existing
 blobs.

 The properties of a bottom blob are also integrated in this module,
 that is, position, velocity, mass and tracer content.  Position and
 velocity are integrated using an adaptive step Runge-Kutta scheme.
 There are several schemes available of varying order.

 The module also recieves blobs that are transferring from the free
 blob dynamic regime to the bottom blob dynamic regime (i.e. free
 blobs that have interacted with topography).
</DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
  Price, J.F., Baringer, M.O'N. (1994) Outflows and deep water production 
  by marginal seas. Progress in Oceanography 33(3), 161-200.
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
  Campin, J-.M., Goosse, H. (1999) Parameterization of a density-driven
  downsloping flow for a coarse-resolution ocean model in z-coordinate.
  Tellus 51A(3), 412-430.
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
  Bogacki, P., Shampine, L.F. (1989) A 3(2) pair of Runge-Kutta formulas.
  Applied Mathematical Letters 2(4), 321-325.
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
  Cash, J.R., Karp, A.H. (1990) A variable order Runge-Kutta method for 
  initial value problems with rapidly varying right-hand sides.
  ACM Transactions on Mathematical Software 16(3), 201-222.
 </REFERENCE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_blob_dynamic_bottom_nml"><DATA NAME="use_this_module" TYPE="logical">
  Must be true to use this module.
  Default is use_this_module=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="blob_overflow_mu" TYPE="real">
  Frictional dissipation rate used for calculating initial
  properties of bottom blobs.  Corresponds to mu in Campin and 
  Goosse (1999).  Units are 1/s.
  Default is blob_overflow_mu=1.0e-4
  </DATA><DATA NAME="blob_overflow_delta" TYPE="real">
  Fraction of a grid cell participating in an overflow event.
  Corresponds to delta in Campin and Goosse (1999).  Dimensionless.
  Default is blob_overflow_mu=1.0e-4
  </DATA><DATA NAME="drag" TYPE="real">
  Coefficient of drag used for bottom stress drag.
  Corresponds to Cd in Price and Baringer (1994). Dimensionless.
  Default is drag=3.0e-3
  </DATA><DATA NAME="det_param" TYPE="real">
  The detrainment parameter (kg m^2/s). 
  Corresponds to Gamma in the notes.
  Default is det_param=5.0e-8

  </DATA><DATA NAME="max_detrainment" TYPE="real">
  The Maximum allowable detrainment velocity (m/s).
  Default is max_detrainment=1.0e-3
  </DATA><DATA NAME="rel_error" TYPE="real">
  Relative error for the RK scheme (dimensionless).
  A smaller number is more accurate, but, 
  is more computationally expensive. Corresponds to
  zeta* in the notes.
  Must be 0&lt;rel_error&lt;=1.0
  Default is rel_error=0.01
  </DATA><DATA NAME="safety_factor" TYPE="real">
  Safety factor for the RK scheme (dimensionless).
  A smaller number should reduce the number
  of rejected steps, but, decreases the locally
  extrapolated step.  Corresponds to varrho in 
  the notes.
  Must be 0&lt;safety_factor&lt;=1.0
  Default is safety_factor=0.8
  </DATA><DATA NAME="minstep" TYPE="real">
  Minimum step size (in seconds) for a blob.
  Default is minstep=9.0
  </DATA><DATA NAME="elastic" TYPE="real">
  The elasticity of a blob's collision with
  the topography.  Corresponds to epsilon in 
  the notes. Should have values 0&lt;=elastic&lt;=1.0
  Values greater than 1 would be super-elastic,
  and values less than 0 would send the blob
  in the opposite direction than it should be 
  going in.
  Default is elastic=1.0
  </DATA><DATA NAME="min_do_levels" TYPE="integer">
  Minimum number of deep ocean levels for
  overflows to be considered.  That is, how many
  k levels lower should the deep ocean water column
  be than the shelf/shallow ocean column.  Value
  must be greater than 0.
  Default is min_do_levels=1
  </DATA><DATA NAME="rho_threshold" TYPE="real">
  The density difference required before a blob
  is formed.  rho_threshold must be greater than
  zero.
  Default is rho_threshold=0.01
  </DATA><DATA NAME="large_speed" TYPE="real">
  A value for error checking.  If the speed of a
  blob exceeds large_speed in any of x,y,z then
  a warning flag is raised.
  Default is large_speed=10.0
  </DATA><DATA NAME="no_rotation" TYPE="real">
  Sets the coriolis parameter to zero regardless
  of latitude
  Default is no_rotation=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="critical_richardson" TYPE="real">
  The critical Richardson number for the entrainment
  velocity.  Default is based on Price and Baringer
  (1994).
  Default is critical_richardson=0.8
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="       constants_mod"/><USE NAME="    diag_manager_mod"/><USE NAME="             fms_mod"/><USE NAME="             mpp_mod"/><USE NAME="     mpp_domains_mod"/><USE NAME=" ocean_blob_util_mod"/><USE NAME="   ocean_density_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_parameters_mod"/><USE NAME="     ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="      ocean_util_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="blob_dynamic_bottom_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialises the dynamic free blobs by checking the namelist and also
 inherited namelists (from ocean_blob_nml).  Also sets up some useful
 constants (including spatially varying constants) - particularly for
 the formation of bottom blobs.  It also allocates memory to special 
 halo=2 masks and sets up the blob buffers for sending blobs from one 
 PE to another.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="blob_dynamic_bottom_update" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 This routine calls the routine to update blob positions.  When
 bitwise_reproduction=.false., it also figures out when to continue
 the integration of blobs that have changed PE's.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="dynamic_update" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 This routine contains the RK scheme used to integrate the position 
 and velocity of blobs.  It also does many checks for (and 
 subsequently handles) things like grounding of blobs, blobs going to
 different PEs, blobs that separate from topography, blobs that 
 detrain to less than small_mass and blobs going outside the compute 
 domain.  

 It also does the interpolation of E system variables to a blob.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="transfer_free_to_bottom" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Takes free blobs that have interacted with topography and turns them
 into bottom blobs.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="dynamic_bottom_form_new" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialises blobs that are formed when an on-shelf/off-shelf
 instability occurs.  The method used for determining an instability
 and the initial conditions are based on that of Campin and Goosse
 (1999).  

 When the density difference between the shallow ocean cell and the 
 deep ocean cell (referenced to the deep ocean cell) exceeds the
 namelist variable rho_threshold, a blob is formed.  The deep ocean
 cell is chosen based on which deep ocean cell (in the k plane)
 the blob topography intersects.

 After formation, the new blobs are added to the bottom blob linked
 list, and, their properties are integrated, starting at time taup1.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="blob_dynamic_bottom_end" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Clears memory to give a nice clean ending to the run.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="packbuffer" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Packs a buffer with all the information needed to send a blob from
 one PE to another.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="unpackbuffer" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Unpacks a received buffer.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="increase_buffer" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Increases the buffer size for sending blobs from one PE to another.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="send_buffer" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Sends a buffer to an adjoining PE
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="receive_buffer" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Receives a buffer from an adjoining PE
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="clear_buffer" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Clears the contents of a buffer
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
