<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE MODULE SYSTEM 
          "/net2/nnz/opt/tools/xmlDoc/share/xmlDoc/schema/fms.dtd">
<MODULE NAME="ocean_blob_static_free_mod" DATE="0000/00/00 00:00:00" HISTORY="http://cobweb.gfdl.noaa.gov/fms-cgi-bin/viewcvs/FMS/ocean/mom5/ocean_blobs"><CONTACT EMAIL="m.bates@student.unsw.edu.au"> Michael L. Bates
</CONTACT><CONTACT EMAIL="GFDL.Climate.Model.Info@noaa.gov"> Stephen M. Griffies
</CONTACT><OVERVIEW>
 This module controls and runs the free static Lagrangian blob 
 parameterisations.
</OVERVIEW><DESCRIPTION>
 There are three available static blob schemes.  None are sanctioned
 for their physical integrity, but they have been important in the 
 development and testing of the Lagrangian framework.

 The first free static scheme emulates the NCON scheme of Cox (1984).
 The second is a scheme that acts in a diffusive manner, while the third
 swaps the properties of adjacent grid cells.  Details of all three schemes
 can be found in Bates et al. (2010).
</DESCRIPTION><INFO><REFERENCE>
 S.M. Griffies, Elements of mom4p1 (2009)
 NOAA/Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory
 </REFERENCE><REFERENCE>
 Cox, M.D., 1984, A Primitive Equation, 3-Dimensional Model of the
 Ocean.  NOAA/Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory
 </REFERENCE></INFO><NAMELIST NAME="ocean_blob_static_free_nml"><DATA NAME="blob_ncon_like" TYPE="logical">
  If true, will use NCon-like formulation. 
  Default blob_ncon_like = .true. 
  </DATA><DATA NAME="blob_diff_like" TYPE="logical">
  If true, will use the diffusion-like formulation. 
  Default is "blob_diff_like=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="blob_swap_like" TYPE="logical">
  If true, will use the swap-like formulation.  
  Default is blob_switch_like=.false.
  </DATA><DATA NAME="ncon_blob" TYPE="integer">
  The number of times that the water column is checked and adjusted
  for instability.
  </DATA></NAMELIST><USE NAME="            fms_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_blob_util_mod"/><USE NAME="  ocean_density_mod"/><USE NAME="    ocean_types_mod"/><USE NAME="ocean_workspace_mod"/><SUBROUTINE NAME="blob_static_free_init" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Initialises the free static schemes.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="blob_static_free" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 A subroutine that is called by the main driver blob module, 
 ocean_blob_mod.  The present module in turn calls the three available
 static schemes.  They are not mutually exclusive and so may be run
 in any combination.

 Note that only the NCON-like scheme has been implemented.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="blob_ncon_like_scheme" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Run the Lagrangian blob model for the NCon-like scheme.  This scheme
 is a static scheme and uses Lagrangian blobs to homogenise adjacent 
 vertical grid cells by by transferring mass and tracer between them.

 This scheme is activated by setting the namelist variable 
 blob_ncon_like=.true.  The number of times that the domain is checked
 for instability is set by the integer namelist variable ncon_blob, of 
 which the default value is 7.

 It is based on the original convective adjustment scheme of 
 Cox (1984).

 See section 2.1 of Bates et al. for further details.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE><SUBROUTINE NAME="blob_static_free_end" INTERFACE=""><DESCRIPTION>
 Ends the free static module.
 </DESCRIPTION></SUBROUTINE></MODULE>
